<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>product on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/product/</link><description>Recent content in product on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/product/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Billion dollar features</title><link>/2021/01/22/billion-dollar-features/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2021/01/22/billion-dollar-features/</guid><description>There&amp;rsquo;s an old story of Steve Jobs meeting Drew Houston in order to acquire Dropbox but after being refused calling Dropbox a feature. Dropbox kept innovating, building a great product, went public and is currently a $9 billion company. Clearly Dropbox proved Steve Jobs wrong. But did it really? Dropbox recently announced a round of layoffs and their stock has dropped 20% since they went public. Even on a personal note I plan on moving my files from Dropbox to Google Drive.</description></item><item><title>Stop charging for support plans</title><link>/2020/12/21/stop-charging-for-support-plans/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/12/21/stop-charging-for-support-plans/</guid><description>My latest rant is against support plans for enterprise software. It&amp;rsquo;s frustrating to be spending hundreds of thousands of dollars on a contract and yet be forced to pay an additional fee for support. Even worse, this additional fee is usually a function of your existing spend.
I understand the rationale - there needs to be a cost to support otherwise everyone has an incentive to escalate and spend is likely correlated with complexity and volume of services used but it just feels as if I&amp;rsquo;m being nickel and dimed.</description></item><item><title>Blame the algorithm</title><link>/2020/12/19/blame-the-algorithm/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/12/19/blame-the-algorithm/</guid><description>Stanford Medicine is in the news for using an &amp;ldquo;algorithm&amp;rdquo; and allocating minimal COVID vaccines to those actually on the frontlines. Instead it supposedly prioritized senior administrators who are working from home. I&amp;rsquo;m sure there&amp;rsquo;s some truth to the algorithm biasing allocation to those who are older but whenever I see someone blame an algorithm my spidey-sense goes off. The algorithm in this case was likely some extremely simple calculation in Excel that could have been easily verified by a human - both before it was run as well as a quick analysis of the results.</description></item><item><title>What do adtech and BGP have in common?</title><link>/2020/12/17/what-do-adtech-and-bgp-have-in-common/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/12/17/what-do-adtech-and-bgp-have-in-common/</guid><description>Despite writing web applications many engineers are not familiar with the infrastructure side of the internet - DNS, BGP, TCP/IP - and yet depend on it all working. Over the years I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a better understanding of the guts of the internet but only in the past few weeks have I discovered Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) on top of BGP. RPKI is meant to add a layer of trust on top of the existing infrastructure which was designed many decades ago without worrying about malicious actors.</description></item><item><title>Substack can evolve into a marketplace</title><link>/2020/12/15/substack-can-evolve-into-a-marketplace/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/12/15/substack-can-evolve-into-a-marketplace/</guid><description>When I first heard of Substack I wasn&amp;rsquo;t too impressed. I fell into the usual engineering trick of thinking it&amp;rsquo;s something that could be &amp;ldquo;built in a weekend&amp;rdquo; but there&amp;rsquo;s a lot going on behind the scenes. Last week I listened to an interview with Substack&amp;rsquo;s CEO, Chris Best, which made me realize the scale and scope of Substack&amp;rsquo;s ambitions.
At the most fundamental level it&amp;rsquo;s a product that allows writers to publish a newsletter - taking care of all the mechanics to let writers write.</description></item><item><title>Do your users delete or archive your email?</title><link>/2020/12/14/do-your-users-delete-or-archive-your-email/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/12/14/do-your-users-delete-or-archive-your-email/</guid><description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve been following this blog you likely know that I subscribe to the Inbox Zero approach to email management. I treat my inbox as a todo list and strive to get it down to zero with varying success. In any case, I spend a lot of time in my email and I noticed an odd pattern to how I deal with handled messages. Some I will delete while I others I&amp;rsquo;ll archive but it happens naturally.</description></item><item><title>Medium is a shopping mall</title><link>/2020/11/14/medium-is-a-shopping-mall/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/11/14/medium-is-a-shopping-mall/</guid><description>I empathize with Medium&amp;rsquo;s need to make money while avoiding ads but as an author it&amp;rsquo;s a bad deal. Medium has great editing and writing tools and a built in audience but if your goal is to share your articles with as broad of an audience as possible the fact that Medium throws up a paywall is a non-starter. Sure you can avoid it by going incognito but how many readers know that?</description></item><item><title>Google and the Apple Watch</title><link>/2020/10/27/google-and-the-apple-watch/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/10/27/google-and-the-apple-watch/</guid><description>If you were to summarize my personal tech stack it would be Google software and Apple hardware. There are a few exceptions but those two companies likely cover the bulk of my technology usage. They&amp;rsquo;re great at what they do within their domains yet the intersection is lacking, especially on the Apple Watch. I suspect Apple is to blame for some of this but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem as if Google doesn&amp;rsquo;t even try to build for the Apple Watch.</description></item><item><title>iOS 14 and local network access</title><link>/2020/09/03/ios-14-and-local-network-access/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/09/03/ios-14-and-local-network-access/</guid><description>Last week I installed the iOS 14 beta since I&amp;rsquo;m curious about what&amp;rsquo;s coming - even if it ends up bricking my phone. I expected it to come with more privacy features but one that surprised me was an alert that apps wanted to &amp;ldquo;find and connect to devices on your local network.&amp;rdquo; This is an obvious one Apple covered this functionality during WWDC. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting seeing which apps request this permission and speculate why.</description></item><item><title>Big money, not big data</title><link>/2020/08/16/big-money-not-big-data/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/08/16/big-money-not-big-data/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s common for companies to complain about the challenges of running big data and how difficult it is. The reality is that unless you&amp;rsquo;re running at massive scale (Google or Facebook) your problems are more to do with big money rather than big data. It&amp;rsquo;s expensive to store, process, and expose terabytes and the difficulty is in doing it cost effectively, not in simply doing it. There are enough modern tools out there across all the cloud providers (AWS, GCP, Azure) and vendors (Snowflake, Databricks) that it&amp;rsquo;s possible to do nearly everything you want but you&amp;rsquo;ll just have to pay for it.</description></item><item><title>Products change, humans stay the same</title><link>/2020/07/30/products-change-humans-stay-the-same/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/07/30/products-change-humans-stay-the-same/</guid><description>While on a quick driving errand a few days ago I decided to listen to the radio for the first time in years. I was quickly hit with a bit of nostalgia - the radio show that was on had one of those &amp;ldquo;First caller to answer this correctly gets Y&amp;rdquo; sessions. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard this thousands of times growing up but this was the first time in a very long time and for whatever reason I immediately thought of both how modern music streaming services no longer have these contests and that a similar need is being met by HQ Trivia.</description></item><item><title>Quibi's problem</title><link>/2020/07/11/quibis-problem/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/07/11/quibis-problem/</guid><description>Everyone loves to bash on Quibi, including me, and yet I feel guilty. We should applaud those who try something new rather than mock it in hindsight. Sure, Quibi raised a ton of money and has an illustrious team but they still deserve respect for attempting to build something from scratch.
Earlier this week I received a Quibi survey and decided to do my part to give them honest feedback. As I was going through the survey that was attempting to understand my usage (or lack of) I developed a personal theory of why it&amp;rsquo;s failing.</description></item><item><title>Dark Mode is for when you run out of real features</title><link>/2020/06/11/dark-mode-is-for-when-you-run-out-of-real-features/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/06/11/dark-mode-is-for-when-you-run-out-of-real-features/</guid><description>I’ve seen a lot of apps launch dark mode and I just don&amp;rsquo;t get it. I&amp;rsquo;m sure part of it is that I mostly stick to the default settings but I can&amp;rsquo;t help but think that if someone is prioritizing dark mode then they must have run out of actually useful features to build. I&amp;rsquo;m being a bit unfair since dark mode can also be a fun side project that someone picks up and may only require changing a few colors around but if it&amp;rsquo;s anything more than that it&amp;rsquo;s an indicator that something is off with their prioritization.</description></item><item><title>Shopify for food delivery</title><link>/2020/05/21/shopify-for-food-delivery/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/05/21/shopify-for-food-delivery/</guid><description>I wrote about the idea of a service that aggregates delivery drivers back in 2018 but given the latest wave of food delivery service bashing I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think of it again. This time around my thoughts are a bit more refined about how to actually build a business but do think there&amp;rsquo;s a real opportunity here, especially after seeing the challenges with the current model.
The existing food delivery apps charge high fees because food delivery is one of the highest costs.</description></item><item><title>A TikTok experience for streaming services</title><link>/2020/03/29/a-tiktok-experience-for-streaming-services/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/03/29/a-tiktok-experience-for-streaming-services/</guid><description>During an interview with Ben Thomson, Eugene Wei has the following response to a question digging into Netflix solving the &amp;ldquo;I just want something on in the background&amp;rdquo; use case:
Yeah, that’s a great point. I also do hope that this macro shock forces the streaming companies to think a little bit harder about innovating on their user interfaces. I still think it’s a little bit of a shame that most of them still present the grid of icons.</description></item><item><title>Zoom's blow up and their financials</title><link>/2020/03/15/zooms-blow-up-and-their-financials/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/03/15/zooms-blow-up-and-their-financials/</guid><description>Zoom has had an incredible rise in the past few weeks as the tech world has shifted to remote work with nearly all meetings occurring over video conferencing. The stock is up 30% over the past month and it&amp;rsquo;s the top app in Apple&amp;rsquo;s app store - all great things! What I&amp;rsquo;m curious about is their current financial performance. Zoom makes money by charging a flat fee per user per month.</description></item><item><title>Paying for improved productivity</title><link>/2020/03/01/paying-for-improved-productivity/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/03/01/paying-for-improved-productivity/</guid><description>Years ago I used to prioritize cost when it came to developer tools. I&amp;rsquo;d resist paying for anything if I could find an open source alternative that worked reasonably well. These days I prioritize my effectiveness and am much more likely to pay for the right tool. A great example of this is my search for a database IDE. I started using Sequel Pro (when I was on a mac) for MySQL and SQuirreL for everything else.</description></item><item><title>Software comparison done right</title><link>/2020/01/24/software-comparison-done-right/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/01/24/software-comparison-done-right/</guid><description>There are a variety of sites out there that exist solely to do comparisons of enterprise software - just type &amp;ldquo;product A vs product B&amp;rdquo; in Google and the first few pages will be littered with results. They all generally follow the same format: a side by side table comparing them feature by feature. Some of the values are factual - for example pricing - while others are based on user reviews.</description></item><item><title>Instagram targeting ads based on likes</title><link>/2020/01/21/instagram-targeting-ads-based-on-likes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/01/21/instagram-targeting-ads-based-on-likes/</guid><description>I noticed a new type of ad targeting behavior on Instagram I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen before - liking someone&amp;rsquo;s shot containing a product leads to a targeted ad containing that product. In my case, a friend posted a picture of an order from the Milk Bar and I gave it a friendly like. A few days later I started seeing ads for the Milk Bar Store. I know it may seem like a manifestation of the Baader-Meinhof phenomenon but I tend to notice ads and am pretty certain I have not seen any Milk Bar ad until I liked that image.</description></item><item><title>Whatever happened to fast software?</title><link>/2020/01/14/whatever-happened-to-fast-software/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/01/14/whatever-happened-to-fast-software/</guid><description>Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just me but it feels as if modern software has been getting slower and slower. My computer is the fastest it has ever been and yet I&amp;rsquo;m more frustrated by the actual performance more than ever. Websites seem slower than they&amp;rsquo;ve ever been and I often find myself typing faster than the letters appear on the screen. Part of the problem is that everything seems to be web-based; in fact, many &amp;ldquo;desktop&amp;rdquo; apps are powered by Electron which is a wrapper around Chromium that makes it easy to write desktop apps.</description></item><item><title>Build for optionality</title><link>/2020/01/03/build-for-optionality/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/01/03/build-for-optionality/</guid><description>I wrote a company wide email back in September titled &amp;ldquo;Building for optionality&amp;rdquo; that describes how our engineering team maintains its impact despite the growing complexity of the business. There are a few TripleLift-specific concepts that I stripped away to make it more approachable but the theme is the same.
For a company that’s growing and changing as quickly as TripleLift, it’s critical to make sure our code is as impactful as possible.</description></item><item><title>Advertising an Airbnb on Instagram</title><link>/2019/12/31/advertising-an-airbnb-on-instagram/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/31/advertising-an-airbnb-on-instagram/</guid><description>I saw an ad for a specific Airbnb on Instagram and just don&amp;rsquo;t understand the economics. It seems unlikely that running this sort of campaign ends up being profitable. I&amp;rsquo;d expect the overlap between the audience targeted and those interested in booking the Airbnb to be extremely low and potentially non-existent.
This Airbnb has a nightly rate of ~$350 and a cleaning fee of $199. If we assume that the average guest books for 3 nights the host is getting ~$1,220 after Airbnb fees ($350 * 0.</description></item><item><title>Self hosted, externally managed</title><link>/2019/12/31/self-hosted-externally-managed/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/31/self-hosted-externally-managed/</guid><description>A couple of days ago I wrote about two questions one can ask when it comes to working with a technology vendor: who&amp;rsquo;s hosting and who&amp;rsquo;s managing?
I find the externally managed but self hosted one interesting. You&amp;rsquo;re giving another company access to your accounts and have full visibility into what they&amp;rsquo;re doing yet you still pay them. An example of this is Databricks. They offer a product akin to Spark-as-a-service along with a variety of bells and whistles that make it much easier to run and manage.</description></item><item><title>Finding parked cars: AWS vs Google computer vision</title><link>/2019/12/29/finding-parked-cars-aws-vs-google-computer-vision/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/29/finding-parked-cars-aws-vs-google-computer-vision/</guid><description>As part of the newly rebooted Parking Spot Finder project I started poking around the cloud computer vision services to see how well they&amp;rsquo;d do at identifying parked cars from an &amp;ldquo;apartment view.&amp;rdquo; The image is pretty straightforward and shows two intersecting streets with a single available parking spot. I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect these services to identify the spot but my hope was that they&amp;rsquo;d be able to identify the cars themselves.</description></item><item><title>Gboard vs iOS swipe keyboard</title><link>/2019/12/28/gboard-vs-ios-swipe-keyboard/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/28/gboard-vs-ios-swipe-keyboard/</guid><description>Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve been blogging left-handed on my phone for the post week I got the chance to try out multiple iOS keyboards all with the hope of improving my typing speed. So far the best one had been Gboard using the swipe. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty similar to the native swipe keyboard offered within iOS but it&amp;rsquo;s just a tad more accurate - especially for shorter words.
Google has the reputation of being the AI and ML leader and it shows in the corrections and predictions.</description></item><item><title>Who's hosting? Who's managing?</title><link>/2019/12/27/whos-hosting-whos-managing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/27/whos-hosting-whos-managing/</guid><description>The end of the year is when companies get inundated with a ton of vendors trying to hit their sales goals. Given this volume comparisons start to become easier and patterns start to emerge. One that I noticed is the gamut of hosting options as well as managed options.
For hosting options, you can choose either the self-hosted option where the software is deployed to your own infrastructure. Alternatively, you can pay the vendor to deploy the code to their infrastructure and expose it through the necessary interfaces.</description></item><item><title>In praise of the simple tech stack</title><link>/2019/12/26/in-praise-of-the-simple-tech-stack/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/26/in-praise-of-the-simple-tech-stack/</guid><description>These days it&amp;rsquo;s so easy to feel as if you&amp;rsquo;re falling behind the tech curve. There&amp;rsquo;s a new tool or technology being released every day and there&amp;rsquo;s a strong temptation to try everything lest you fall behind.
That&amp;rsquo;s why it was so refreshing to come across &amp;ldquo;The boring technology behind a one-person Internet company.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s a post written by Wenbin Fang, the founder and CEO of ListenNotes.com, and is exactly what you think it is.</description></item><item><title>Disney's hostile takeover</title><link>/2019/12/16/disneys-hostile-takeover/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/16/disneys-hostile-takeover/</guid><description>While watching The Imagineering Story I discovered that Disney was the target of a hostile takeover attempt in the 1980s. This is shocking given how dominant Disney currently is and it&amp;rsquo;s incredible that it came that close to being broken up and sold as individual pieces. Luckily, Disney withstood the attempt but this was a wakeup call that led to Michael Eisner rekindling the Disney magic.
There&amp;rsquo;s a ton written about the attempt by people better suited but what I find fascinating is that the entire breakup attempt goes against the entire strategy Walt Disney put together in 1957.</description></item><item><title>TabNine</title><link>/2019/12/15/tabnine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/15/tabnine/</guid><description>I’m a heavy Visual Studio Code user and one of my favorite plugins has been TabNine. I use VS Code to hack around across a variety of languages in addition to note-taking and TabNine makes me significantly more productive. It&amp;rsquo;s a language-agnostic autocompleter that relies on machine learning rather than predefined heuristics and analyzes whatever you type in order to offer you a variety of suggestions. It&amp;rsquo;s similar to GMail&amp;rsquo;s new autocomplete functionality but in your editor.</description></item><item><title>Disney+</title><link>/2019/12/13/disney-/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/13/disney-/</guid><description>I signed up for the Disney+ account as soon as it launched. The primary reason was for The Mandalorian but I&amp;rsquo;m also enjoying The Imagineering Story and access to The Simpsons archive. My biggest surprise was how polished it all was. It&amp;rsquo;s a brand new product and it&amp;rsquo;s impressive what the team has done. It had a few hiccups at launch has but has been extremely smooth since then.
I use it on the Fire TV Stick so can’t speak to the other platforms but it&amp;rsquo;s simpler, and yet more polished than Netflix.</description></item><item><title>Search within Google search</title><link>/2019/12/11/search-within-google-search/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/11/search-within-google-search/</guid><description>Google Search has evolved quite a bit from a single search bar and now contains a ton of modules to give users what they want as quickly as they can. This manifests itself in sections optimized for different verticals: sports, travel, shopping, weather, Wikipedia, and really anything that can be somewhat structured.
I discovered a new module yesterday when doing a search for an online thesaurus. Rather than just have a link to thesaurus.</description></item><item><title>Improving product reviews</title><link>/2019/11/24/improving-product-reviews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/11/24/improving-product-reviews/</guid><description>Modern ecommerce is predicated on having proper product reviews. Every site that sells online depends on them and yet they&amp;rsquo;re still far from what they can be. The reviews I&amp;rsquo;ve seen tend to be done when a product arrives rather than after years of use. Similarly, manufactures may change and shift production over time so early reviews will highlight the high quality of a product while latter reviews will bemoan the lack of quality.</description></item><item><title>Rebirth of digital piracy?</title><link>/2019/11/17/rebirth-of-digital-piracy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/11/17/rebirth-of-digital-piracy/</guid><description>The best jokes have an element of truth to them and earlier today I came across a comic that was a great example.
Source: Hoppy_Doodle @ reddit.com
It&amp;rsquo;s surprising how true that is. Many of us have been cable TV free for years and were content paying a monthly internet bill along with Netflix and maybe one or two additional subscriptions. Now it feels as if there&amp;rsquo;s a new streaming service launching every few months with the costs adding up to be equivalent to a traditional cable TV bill.</description></item><item><title>GitHub's security automation</title><link>/2019/10/26/githubs-security-automation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/10/26/githubs-security-automation/</guid><description>I have a variety of old projects up on GitHub and recently noticed pull requests being opened from &amp;ldquo;dependabot&amp;rdquo; to fix security vulnerabilities in old requirements files. Turns out it&amp;rsquo;s a new feature offered by GitHub that scans repos and submits patches to upgrade insecure versions. This is a great idea - there&amp;rsquo;s very little chance that I&amp;rsquo;d go through my old and unmaintained repos to upgrade their dependencies but I&amp;rsquo;d definitely approve and merge a PR that upgrades a few of my libraries.</description></item><item><title>SSO and SAAS pricing</title><link>/2019/09/28/sso-and-saas-pricing/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/09/28/sso-and-saas-pricing/</guid><description>For a very long time I wondered why SSO was always listed as a premium feature across nearly every enterprise software pricing page but no more! When you’re small it’s simple to manage permissions and the costs of screwing up are far smaller. Large companies, on the other hand, have complex organization structures with hundreds of employees that use a wide range of applications and access controls are a real concern.</description></item><item><title>Where's the new iPhone SE?</title><link>/2019/09/12/wheres-the-new-iphone-se/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/09/12/wheres-the-new-iphone-se/</guid><description>After the new iPhone announcement there&amp;rsquo;s been a bunch of commentary around the desire to come up with a new version of the SE, a smaller factor phone. Fred Wilson posted a short post about it and it was quickly picked up and spread across various forums, such as Hacker News. The discussions generally ranged around the market size and how it&amp;rsquo;s not just worth it but I suspect a big part is the hardware.</description></item><item><title>Disney+</title><link>/2019/08/24/disney-/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/08/24/disney-/</guid><description>Yesterday the internet blew up after Disney&amp;rsquo;s announcement of a new series, The Mandalorian, that would be available as a part of their new streaming service, Disney+. I watched the trailer and as expected it hit all the right Star Wars nostalgia points. The show itself wasn&amp;rsquo;t what stood out. Instead it was the closing scene where Disney highlights what Disney+ includes: Disney, Pixar, Marvel, Star Wars, and National Geographic.</description></item><item><title>What do airlines and LinkedIn have in common?</title><link>/2019/08/22/what-do-airlines-and-linkedin-have-in-common/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/08/22/what-do-airlines-and-linkedin-have-in-common/</guid><description>Supposedly airlines could make the economy seats much better than they are without a significant investment but purposefully do not in order to encourage people that can afford business or first class to choose business or first class. Perversely, this makes sense. If economy is only slightly worse than business then I&amp;rsquo;d be willing to save quite a bit of money by choosing economy for a worse experience. Yet if the economy seats were significantly worse then I&amp;rsquo;d pay a premium for business.</description></item><item><title>A more efficient Google Calendar</title><link>/2019/07/21/a-more-efficient-google-calendar/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/21/a-more-efficient-google-calendar/</guid><description>Google Calendar is starting to become one of my favorite Google products. They&amp;rsquo;re constantly shipping new features that keep on making it easier and more efficient to use. One of the most recent improvements is the ability to create a fully featured event directly from the calendar screen. One of my biggest use cases is to schedule a meeting with someone which requires knowing both their availability and the availability of a room.</description></item><item><title>A more efficient Google Calendar backup</title><link>/2019/07/21/a-more-efficient-google-calendar-backup/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/21/a-more-efficient-google-calendar-backup/</guid><description>Google Calendar is starting to become one of my favorite Google products. They&amp;rsquo;re constantly shipping new features that keep on making it easier and more efficient to use. One of the most recent improvements is the ability to create a fully featured event directly from the calendar screen. One of my biggest use cases is to schedule a meeting with someone which requires knowing both their availability and the availability of a room.</description></item><item><title>Why is your Confluence in Polish?</title><link>/2019/07/19/why-is-your-confluence-in-polish/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/19/why-is-your-confluence-in-polish/</guid><description>Despite not speaking any Polish, I changed my Confluence language to Polish earlier this week to finally fix a problem that&amp;rsquo;s been bugging me for years. Confluence has the concept of a &amp;ldquo;date lozenge&amp;rdquo; which allows you to add a date via a helpful calendar and gives it a nice looking format. We decided to use these lozenges to track dates in our system since it improves consistency and they do get special treatment in Confluence and lead to a few neat features - for example being able to use them as due dates in tasks.</description></item><item><title>Substack vs Medium</title><link>/2019/07/17/substack-vs-medium/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/17/substack-vs-medium/</guid><description>I heard about Substack for the first time today while reading the Stratechery newsletter. For those not familiar (like me before today!), Substack is a startup that makes it easier for individual content creators to create and monetize newsletters with the goal of empowering them to build their own media empires.
As I read the article I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think about the struggles Medium has had since its founding. It started as a blogging platform and had a variety of challenges with monetization over the years.</description></item><item><title>Credit card merchant fees</title><link>/2019/07/06/credit-card-merchant-fees/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/06/credit-card-merchant-fees/</guid><description>A Stratechery post covering Facebook&amp;rsquo;s cryptocurrency launch mentions that credit card merchant fees are generally a flat $0.29 fee plus 1.5~3.5% of the transaction. The argument is that the market is efficient and if there was a way to drop them one of the credit card providers would have to gain an advantage.
I don&amp;rsquo;t buy this argument. I don&amp;rsquo;t have the history of merchant fees but my suspicion is that they changed minimally, if at all, over the past few decades despite the massive amount of data being collected and the processing capability to go with it.</description></item><item><title>Combine registration and sign in</title><link>/2019/07/02/combine-registration-and-sign-in/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/02/combine-registration-and-sign-in/</guid><description>The goal of nearly every site or app is to get users to engage as quickly as possible. That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s surprising that so many sites have a separate flow for registration versus sign in. There&amp;rsquo;s no good reason that these two flows shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be combined.
A part of nearly every registration is entering an email and password so why not make them the first step of the sign up process?</description></item><item><title>Sign In with Apple</title><link>/2019/07/01/sign-in-with-apple/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/01/sign-in-with-apple/</guid><description>Apple recently made the announcement that apps that provide third party login will also be required to offer a Sign in with Apple option. Apple will then, in turn, anonymize the email address and thus anomyze the user. The idea here being that the app will only have access to the random email generated by Apple and all email will have to be proxied through the email address generated by Apple.</description></item><item><title>Polaroid and Dr. Edwin Land</title><link>/2019/04/30/polaroid-and-dr.-edwin-land/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/04/30/polaroid-and-dr.-edwin-land/</guid><description>I recently finished A Triumph of Genius: Edwin Land, Polaroid, and the Kodak Patent War which starts with a wonderful biography of Edwin Land and ends with a ton of detail about the Polaroid/Kodak lawsuit. Polaroid was a remarkable company and it&amp;rsquo;s both amazing that it&amp;rsquo;s no longer around and remarkable that the modern tech world doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to appreciate Polaroid and Edwin Land. We put Steve Jobs on a pedestal but Edwin Land was the precursor.</description></item><item><title>Free as in puppy</title><link>/2019/04/23/free-as-in-puppy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/04/23/free-as-in-puppy/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve known about &amp;ldquo;free as in beer&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;free as in speech&amp;rdquo; for a while now but only recently have I learned about &amp;ldquo;free as in puppy.&amp;rdquo; I came across the phrase while reading a Stratechery article describing various ways of thinking about regulation. The idea is that just like getting a free puppy, you get it for free but it comes with a significant long term cost.
I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of the phrase and it highlights a very common tradeoff we make, especially in engineering.</description></item><item><title>Airbnb and HotelTonight</title><link>/2019/03/17/airbnb-and-hoteltonight/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/03/17/airbnb-and-hoteltonight/</guid><description>A few weeks ago Airbnb announced that they would be acquiring Hotel Tonight. This was a surprise - throughout its history Airbnb has made a point to compete with hotels and my gut was that hotels would not be too happy to partner with a competitor. I understand that Airbnb is trying to grow before their inevitable IPO and to do so they need to invest in growth. I also subscribe to the argument that from their standpoint they’re focused on giving people a place to stay and not necessarily that concerned with the exact medium - private rental or hotel or whatever else.</description></item><item><title>LinkedIn's terrible messaging experience</title><link>/2019/03/10/linkedins-terrible-messaging-experience/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/03/10/linkedins-terrible-messaging-experience/</guid><description>This is a bit of a ranty post but it’s incredible how poor the LinkedIn messaging experience is. If anyone sends me a LinkedIn message I get an email telling me that so-and-so sent me a message. To read the actual message I need to clickthrough to get to the LinkedIn site. I get it, they want to increase engagement and have me access the site and show me something new.</description></item><item><title>Dropbox should drop the freemium model</title><link>/2019/02/28/dropbox-should-drop-the-freemium-model/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/02/28/dropbox-should-drop-the-freemium-model/</guid><description>This is a bit heretical but I suspect Dropbox would make more money if it moved away from a freemium model. I have been a user of the free Dropbox account for multiple years now and due to their various promotions have gotten my free storage up to 6GB and yet I use just under 4GB. I don’t use it to store images but instead use it to store important documents that I want to both keep safe but also frequently access across multiple devices.</description></item><item><title>Netflix recommendation system failure</title><link>/2019/02/10/netflix-recommendation-system-failure/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/02/10/netflix-recommendation-system-failure/</guid><description>I have zero interest in horror or drama and have never watched any of them on Netflix yet Netflix decided to automatically start playing the gory intro to their new Ted Bundy series. I understand their desire to highlight their shows but autoplaying something that gory just seems like a terrible decision, especially given my viewing history.
Many people will launch Netflix with their families around and having something so graphically violent greet you is a surefire way to lose fans and subscribers.</description></item><item><title>A personal DSP</title><link>/2019/02/09/a-personal-dsp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/02/09/a-personal-dsp/</guid><description>A common refrain from people who use adblock is that they’d be willing to pay for the content if it were an option and only use adblock to avoid the tracking and slow site speed. The desire is to have a way to see how much a website is generating from their visit and give the publisher that money directly. That way the publisher gets the equivalent amount of money as they would otherwise and the user gets to avoid ads.</description></item><item><title>Finally, some price increases</title><link>/2019/02/02/finally-some-price-increases/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/02/02/finally-some-price-increases/</guid><description>For as long as I can remember it felt that there was this hidden rule that companies cannot raise prices or risk mass customer abandonment. Yet the past few few months we’ve seen two major companies increase prices - Atlassian and Netflix - without any adverse effects. The products are improving and are offering more functionality so it’s only fair that the prices increase. This is a welcome sign and I hope it leads to companies starting to invest significantly more in improving their existing products with the expectation that they’ll be able to raise prices in line with the additional value they’re bringing.</description></item><item><title>Buying Kindle books on iOS</title><link>/2019/01/12/buying-kindle-books-on-ios/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/01/12/buying-kindle-books-on-ios/</guid><description>Earlier this week I finished an ebook on the train and wanted to purchase another one for the way back while waiting in the station. Remarkably, Apple, a company that emphasizes and takes pride in its user experience, does not make this easy. It turns out that the Kindle app on iOS does not allow you to actually purchase a book and isn’t even allowed to link to a page where it can be purchased.</description></item><item><title>GitHub's new plan</title><link>/2019/01/08/githubs-new-plan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/01/08/githubs-new-plan/</guid><description>Earlier today GitHub announced that they would make a significant change to their plans: a free plan would now be able to have private repos. I’m likely one of the many GitHub users who host their personal projects on GitHub with many being private. Some of these are projects I’m just not ready to release while others are proprietary scripts or private DevOps code. I was on the $7/mo Pro plan and downgraded to the free plan.</description></item><item><title>Amazon vs Walmart</title><link>/2018/12/30/amazon-vs-walmart/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/30/amazon-vs-walmart/</guid><description>One of the most exciting business battles is Amazon vs Walmart and I’m interested in seeing what happens in 2019. As I’m writing this Amazon has a market cap of $723B while Walmart is at $268. At the same time, Amazon’s 2017 revenue was $178B while Walmart’s was $486B. The market views them as two completely different businesses and that’s fair - Walmart is a traditional retailer while Amazon has its hands in a variety of businesses - ranging from retail, to a marketplace, to a cloud hosting provider.</description></item><item><title>Twenty seconds makes all the difference</title><link>/2018/12/30/twenty-seconds-makes-all-the-difference/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/30/twenty-seconds-makes-all-the-difference/</guid><description>I recently switched from a 2015 Macbook Pro to a new ThinkPad with Ubuntu and one of the most noticeable differences is how much faster this blog builds. A few years ago I moved this blog over to AMP to improve its load times. I don’t want to go into the details of AMP but in order to get the performance wins all styling is inlined - that means that instead of linking to a CSS file the CSS rules are explicitly defined on each page.</description></item><item><title>Wired headphones</title><link>/2018/12/29/wired-headphones/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/29/wired-headphones/</guid><description>I left my Bluetooth headphones at home this morning and ended up borrowing a wired pair during the day. I forgot how easy it is to just be able to plug in and go - no waiting for the headphones to turn on, no waiting for the Bluetooth to connect, and no having to deal with selecting the proper audio out channel. The convenience of Bluetooth outweighs the costs but it was a stark reminder of how much more robust and simpler tools used to be.</description></item><item><title>Calendly</title><link>/2018/12/28/calendly/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/28/calendly/</guid><description>Over the years I’ve received a ton of Calendly links - it’s an application that integrates with your calendar and hosts a personal page that allows others to book time on your calendar. As a user it’s great since it offloads scheduling responsibility from you to others. At the same time, I was was always bothered by the fact that that effort was externalized to me despite it actually being more efficient for both sides.</description></item><item><title>Happy holidays from Visual Studio Code</title><link>/2018/12/25/happy-holidays-from-visual-studio-code/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/25/happy-holidays-from-visual-studio-code/</guid><description>Visual Studio Code has been my go-to editor since the beginning of 2017 and I’m a huge fan. They reinforced my belief with a little Easter egg earlier today to celebrate Christmas. The settings icon in the bottom right corner got a special Santa hat and clicking on it gives you an additional menu option labeled “Happy Holidays!” which gives you a friendly holiday message along with some falling snow.</description></item><item><title>Quora's revenue model</title><link>/2018/12/23/quoras-revenue-model/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/23/quoras-revenue-model/</guid><description>While browsing a Hacker News thread about Quora I came across the following exchange:
I had always assumed Quora made money through ads and didn’t even consider that they had another revenue stream. The Hacker News thread indicates that they have a substantial revenue stream coming from selling the Q&amp;amp;A data to AI/ML companies but I haven’t been able to find anything else that supports this. Part of the difficulty in searching for results is that just by typing in “Quora” the results are biased towards Quora itself.</description></item><item><title>Edge moving to Chromium</title><link>/2018/12/22/edge-moving-to-chromium/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/22/edge-moving-to-chromium/</guid><description>I’m a bit late to the party but it’s unbelievable that Microsoft is going to move future versions of Edge to be built on top of Chromium. This is shocking. I can’t separate Internet Explorer from Microsoft. In fact, Microsoft built, launched, and bundled Internet Explorer to drive Netscape into the ground which led to the famous Microsoft antitrust case. It feels as if Microsoft is giving up on Internet Explorer and it’s incredibly surprising.</description></item><item><title>I finally tried an electric scooter</title><link>/2018/12/18/i-finally-tried-an-electric-scooter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/18/i-finally-tried-an-electric-scooter/</guid><description>I live in the NYC area which has Citi Bike but doesn’t allow any scooter companies to operate. In fact it actually disallows any electric bikes/scooters/skateboards/hoverboards and only makes an exception for pedal-assisted bikes. And since I haven’t been traveling much the closest I could get to trying an electric scooter was reading the endless series of articles about them.
Luckily for me I went on a vacation to Mexico City and got the chance to try a Lime scooter.</description></item><item><title>Scenepeek</title><link>/2018/12/12/scenepeek/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/12/scenepeek/</guid><description>Way back when as I was just leaving the finance world to go into tech I attempted a startup with a friend called Scenepeek. The goal was to constantly aggregate all of a city’s events and make them easily searchable and discoverable by people who were looking to do something. Since both of us were in NYC and there are always a ton of events we decided that it would be the perfect candidate.</description></item><item><title>Automatic login</title><link>/2018/12/08/automatic-login/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/08/automatic-login/</guid><description>This is somewhat heretical but whenever I receive an email that has a link behind a login I wish clicking the link would automatically log me in. I’ve spent more time than I’d like to admit typing my username and password on various sites and too often have had to do it multiple times to get the password right. It would be amazing if clicking a link on an email would automatically log me in and navigate to the linked page.</description></item><item><title>Fat specs, light stories</title><link>/2018/12/01/fat-specs-light-stories/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/01/fat-specs-light-stories/</guid><description>Most modern software companies use some form of agile as their software development process. There are a variety of different approaches and forms out there and each company ends up with a style that works for them. One of the core beliefs I’ve developed is that stories should be kept light and that time and effort should be spent on the product requirement documents and specs. Investing in the PRDs and specs encourages everyone to understand the high level problem being solved and how the various pieces of the solutions fit together.</description></item><item><title>A delivery aggregation service</title><link>/2018/11/29/a-delivery-aggregation-service/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/11/29/a-delivery-aggregation-service/</guid><description>Full disclosure: I know very little about the food delivery space so this is more speculative than anything rooted in reality.
Given how many companies are doing food delivery it seems there should be a single delivery aggregation service that combines all of them to act as the perfect dispatcher for drivers. If I’m delivering food on behalf of Uber Eats, DoorDash, Postmates, Grubhub, and the countless others I missed it would make sense for me to be able to pick up from as many nearby restaurants as possible and then deliver to as many colocated locations as possible.</description></item><item><title>An ad on the Google search homepage</title><link>/2018/11/26/an-ad-on-the-google-search-homepage/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/11/26/an-ad-on-the-google-search-homepage/</guid><description>Turns out not even Google is immune from the pressures of Cyber Monday. As minimal as the Google search homepage is they still made the effort to have a callout, however slight, to promote their Cyber Monday deals. A while back I read an article that calculated how much additional revenue Google would be able to generate if they put ads on their homepage. I don’t recall the exact number or the details but I imagine it’s a massive amount.</description></item><item><title>Adding optionality to products</title><link>/2018/11/24/adding-optionality-to-products/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/11/24/adding-optionality-to-products/</guid><description>Building products involves making countless decisions. One of the biggest is defining the functionality and how it should be exposed to the users. In my mind, answers to this question like on a spectrum. On one extreme you have the “take what you can get” approach where the functionality is exposed with no customization and no advanced features but the experience is optimized for one specific use case. As an example of this think of the original Google search - a single search field, minimal search functionality, and two buttons.</description></item><item><title>What messaging war?</title><link>/2018/11/14/what-messaging-war/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/11/14/what-messaging-war/</guid><description>Apparently there’s a “messaging war” going on among the dozens of apps and social networks, all competing to be the dominant messaging app. There really are a ton of these. I have a folder on my phone dedicated to messaging and it contains Apple Messages, Google Hangouts, WhatsApp, WeChat, Telegram, Facebook Messenger, and Signal. In addition, Twitter, Instagram, and Snapchat all have messaging functionality. Adding these up I have 10 messaging apps on my phone.</description></item><item><title>A UX gem in Google Slides</title><link>/2018/11/13/a-ux-gem-in-google-slides/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/11/13/a-ux-gem-in-google-slides/</guid><description>I’m a sucker for subtle UX gems and Google continues to amaze me. While working on a presentation using the Slides product I had to modify the colors of a few objects. The UX for this is usually pretty normal - you select the object, hit the icon to modify the color, and choose a new color. Usually it’s slightly better and you get to see the existing color. What surprised me with the Google Slides experience is that I didn’t just see the existing color but also saw the previously picked color.</description></item><item><title>Gmail's autocomplete</title><link>/2018/10/29/gmails-autocomplete/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/10/29/gmails-autocomplete/</guid><description>Ever since I’ve been managing I’ve spent an inordinate amount of time in my inbox. What’s both sad and amazing is how accurate the new Gmail autocompletions (officially called Smart Compose) have gotten. They’re incredibly accurate for common phrases and are likely leveraging very similar technology to what Google is using for their autocomplete search. It’s great for finishing off that last sentence and even acts as a real time phrase thesaurus that helps suggest alternate phrasing.</description></item><item><title>Just ship it</title><link>/2018/10/25/just-ship-it/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/10/25/just-ship-it/</guid><description>I don’t know whether it’s the pace of modern life or something else but I no longer have a good intuition for recent events. Things that happened a few months ago feel as if they happened a year ago and things that happened a year ago feel as if they happened multiple years ago. An example of this was Twitter increasing a tweet’s character limit to 280. Try to guess when they increased the limit?</description></item><item><title>Google Calendar: Constantly shipping</title><link>/2018/08/15/google-calendar-constantly-shipping/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/08/15/google-calendar-constantly-shipping/</guid><description>It’s impressive when companies constantly churn out products and features and it’s even more impressive the larger the company. In my mind this used to be Amazon but lately I’ve been surprised by how often Google Calendar is updated. It feels as if every month there’s at least one update that I accidentally discover and get a pleasant surprise.
Google Calendar underwent a major redesign earlier this year and it seemed to have been the foundation for the recent improvements.</description></item><item><title>Privacy vs user experience</title><link>/2018/07/29/privacy-vs-user-experience/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/07/29/privacy-vs-user-experience/</guid><description>These days it feels as if every tech behemoth is competing with every other tech behemoth but one of the more interesting battles has been between Google and Apple. Google is the accepted leader in ML and AI and they leverage it to offer a better and constantly improving user experience. Apple, on the other hand, has been stressing that unlike Google it doesn’t make money off of data mining your data and is instead focused on privacy.</description></item><item><title>Bulk discounts hurt competition</title><link>/2018/07/22/bulk-discounts-hurt-competition/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/07/22/bulk-discounts-hurt-competition/</guid><description>While reading yet another article about scooter startups I came across an obvious quote by Gao Lufeng, CEO of Segway-Ninebot, the leading scooter manufacturer: “As one of the biggest battery buyers, we have the bargaining power to get the lowest price in the market.”
This is obvious and we see it everywhere: buying in bulk gets you a discount. As a consumer I can go to Amazon and look at any item and the per unit price when buying a single item is going to be higher than when buying a pack.</description></item><item><title>Rise of microbrands</title><link>/2018/04/28/rise-of-microbrands/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/04/28/rise-of-microbrands/</guid><description>While browsing Instagram the other day I saw an ad for Optimum. Despite it being for Optimum the ad showed a sports clip that could have just as easily been on a highlight real or a a trailer for a sports movie. In fact, if it weren’t associated with Optimum maybe I would have even clicked on it.
Having a strong brand is incredibly valuable - think Coca Cola. A weak brand (think amy ISP), on the other hand, is incredibly damaging.</description></item><item><title>Retrieving Kindle highlights</title><link>/2018/02/25/retrieving-kindle-highlights/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/02/25/retrieving-kindle-highlights/</guid><description>At this point I’ve moved most the majority of my reading to a Kindle. If I want to read a book I’ll only get a physical version if the Kindle version is unavailable. It’s often cheaper, immediately available, takes up no space, and comes with a variety of annotation abilities. My biggest frustration has been how difficult it’s been to export my highlights. I will often highlight interesting passages and quotes and every few weeks will dump them into a giant text file that I will occasionally reference or search.</description></item><item><title>Optimize for keyboard shortcuts</title><link>/2018/02/10/optimize-for-keyboard-shortcuts/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/02/10/optimize-for-keyboard-shortcuts/</guid><description>I’m a big believer of offering keyboard-only experiences to your power users. In fact, I don’t think it’s possible to build a loved productivity application without keyboard shortcuts. Productivity applications are all about productivity and keyboard shortcuts are what give your users power and speed. The mouse and menus are easier for newcomers but those that stick with the application inevitably need the speed that comes from shortcuts.
The ultimate example of this is Excel.</description></item><item><title>MoviePass: A fascinating business model</title><link>/2018/01/28/moviepass-a-fascinating-business-model/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/01/28/moviepass-a-fascinating-business-model/</guid><description>Given my lack of cultural knowledge the fact that I’ve heard of MoviePass should be a sign that it’s a big deal. I came across a fascinating article today about MoviePass’s revenue model - they charge just under $10/month and in return you get unlimited access to movies in theaters. What’s remarkable is that it seems MoviePass doesn’t actually have a subsidized relationship with theaters and just pays theaters the full ticket price.</description></item><item><title>Send a shirt, get a shirt</title><link>/2017/12/25/send-a-shirt-get-a-shirt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/12/25/send-a-shirt-get-a-shirt/</guid><description>Despite being an early tech adopter I avoid buying clothes online. At first the justification was that I didn’t want to deal with the cost of returns but these days nearly every retailer offers free returns. At this point it’s more habit than anything else and given how infrequently I buy clothes I’d rather just do it in person when necessary.
The one service that I wish existed, and I’m sure it does somewhere, is a place where I can send some existing clothes that I know fit me perfectly and then have them used as the basis for new, custom made clothes.</description></item><item><title>More intelligent credit card merchant rates</title><link>/2017/12/14/more-intelligent-credit-card-merchant-rates/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/12/14/more-intelligent-credit-card-merchant-rates/</guid><description>While reading today’s Stratechery update on Patreon changing their pricing model I came across the following passage:
Of course this wasn’t great for creators: payments made for a creation released on November 2 wouldn’t land in creators’ bank accounts until some time after December 1; the reasoning, though, was clear — credit card fees. Here I can certainly bring personal experience to bear: credit card fees are really expensive (they are by far Stratechery’s largest expense)!</description></item><item><title>Ride sharing ride bailing</title><link>/2017/11/20/ride-sharing-ride-bailing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/11/20/ride-sharing-ride-bailing/</guid><description>One of the more frustrating modern, first-world problems is booking a Lyft or an Uber ride and having the driver cancel the ride a soon as they find out where you’re going. While against policy it is a rational decision by the driver. Why agree to a trip somewhere where it&amp;rsquo;ll be difficult to pick up another passenger and then have to return to where you started and incur a toll?</description></item><item><title>Scaling meal kit distribution</title><link>/2017/09/06/scaling-meal-kit-distribution/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/09/06/scaling-meal-kit-distribution/</guid><description>Earlier today I read a neat article covering the meal-kit delivery space and how give Blue Apron’s lackluster performance on the public market the still-private competitors are exploring alternative options, including partnering with grocery stores and general CPG companies. I hadn’t thought much about the space but it’s a great idea.
Fresh food is a difficult business that benefits heavily from scale. Buying in bulk gives you significant price discounts and being able to have high throughput reduces the amount of food that spoils.</description></item><item><title>Google Docs vs Confluence</title><link>/2017/08/08/google-docs-vs-confluence/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/08/08/google-docs-vs-confluence/</guid><description>I’ve been a happy user of Google Docs for years now and have yet to find another product that makes collaboration that easy or simple. It’s a well designed product with a ton of shortcuts that make it incredibly easy to be exceptionally productive. I can dive in and quickly leave a few comments as well as assign some todos knowing that the relevant folk will be notified. And for a very long time I’ve been using it for the bulk of my writing - including specs, design documents, and general note taking.</description></item><item><title>A Google Docs efficiency win</title><link>/2017/07/24/a-google-docs-efficiency-win/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/07/24/a-google-docs-efficiency-win/</guid><description>Old Google Docs behavior
I’m an efficiency fiend and love seeing my heavily used products updated with any and all functionality that make them a tad easier to use. A few weeks ago, Google Docs, one of my most heavily used applications - in fact where I’m writing this very post - made a minor change to the “Move to” functionality that created one of these small efficiency wins. Before the change, clicking the small folder icon while in a document would show a menu with the item’s current location and a “Move this item” option.</description></item><item><title>Apple's ARKit</title><link>/2017/06/22/apples-arkit/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/06/22/apples-arkit/</guid><description>During this year’s WWDC Apple announced ARKit, a development framework that simplifies the ability of incorporating augmented reality into your app. I’ve been fascinated by this for a while and took a stab at getting their code running. I’ve only dabbled in iOS development so the bulk of the effort involved getting the latest Xcode beta and then discovering to run the full example I needed to upgrade my phone to run the iOS 11 beta.</description></item><item><title>Engineering, product, and design</title><link>/2017/05/27/engineering-product-and-design/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/05/27/engineering-product-and-design/</guid><description>The best products are built when engineering, product, and designers work together. When things are running smoothly each brings skill, knowledge, and experience the others cannot. When things are running poorly the teams do not respect or trust each other and question the others’ approach and decision making. Inevitably this leads to a flawed product that doesn’t solve customer needs and gets replaced by one that does. It’s possible to ride previous success through inertia, marketing, and price but to grow in the modern era you need to focus on product.</description></item><item><title>IVR to SMS</title><link>/2017/05/25/ivr-to-sms/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/05/25/ivr-to-sms/</guid><description>Seems it’s all about messaging now and yet we somehow still have the ridiculous automated call systems which the industry calls interactive voice response. Every single person I know hates having to call a customer support number only to hear a robotic voice that requires a series of frustrated enunciations to get what you wanted. I understand that it’s a huge win in terms of cost savings since you’re replacing people with software but moving over to SMS and asynchronous messaging would make it a better experience at an even lower cost.</description></item><item><title>AMP and subscription paywalls</title><link>/2017/04/16/amp-and-subscription-paywalls/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/04/16/amp-and-subscription-paywalls/</guid><description>A variety of publishers are adopting Accelerated Mobile Pages (AMP) to speed up the performance of their sites on mobile. In fact, I’m using AMP to power my entire blog on both desktop and mobile and it’s significantly faster than my old, heavyweight site. But I’m a small time blogger and to get real publishers on board AMP needs to support a variety of monetization options - including ads and subscriptions - that are able to generate the same revenue they’re getting without AMP.</description></item><item><title>Quality over quantity: NextDoor vs Craigslist</title><link>/2017/04/08/quality-over-quantity-nextdoor-vs-craigslist/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/04/08/quality-over-quantity-nextdoor-vs-craigslist/</guid><description>Last weekend my wife and decided that we needed to upgrade our couch and in our eagerness decided that we wanted it delivered as soon as possible which happened to be Friday (yesterday). This led us to the question of what to do with our existing couch. The pragmatist in me decided that we should list it on Craigslist and NextDoor for $300 and see who would bite but after a few days without any response it became clear that if we wanted it gone soon it would need to be free.</description></item><item><title>Fulfillment by Amazon counterfeiting</title><link>/2017/03/26/fulfillment-by-amazon-counterfeiting/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/03/26/fulfillment-by-amazon-counterfeiting/</guid><description>Recently I’ve come across a few articles describing the supposedly massive amount of counterfeiting happening on Amazon. The way it works is that Amazon offers a Fulfillment by Amazon (called FBA) option where a merchant sends their items to Amazon’s warehouse which is then eligible for Prime shipping since it’s just going to be shipped by Amazon. The way Amazon implements this is by commingling the items - so if two merchants send Amazon the same item Amazon will treat it as the same item when it comes to consumers.</description></item><item><title>Amazon's peer to peer marketplace</title><link>/2016/12/31/amazons-peer-to-peer-marketplace/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/12/31/amazons-peer-to-peer-marketplace/</guid><description>It looks as if Amazon is entering yet another market - the local peer to peer marketplace. They just launched a peer to peer marketplace in Bangalore. The pitch is incredibly simple - you create a listing and it’s listed on Amazon. As soon as it’s sold Amazon will pick up the item and deliver it to the buyer. I’ve used Craigslist a ton in the past and coordinating the delivery and handoff was always a frustrating experience.</description></item><item><title>The NFL abroad</title><link>/2016/10/30/the-nfl-abroad/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/10/30/the-nfl-abroad/</guid><description>NFL viewership is down 10% this season and I understand the desire to grow the brand and the sport abroad. It seems misguided to take a product that’s declining in popularity and rather than fixing the core problems to try to grow it as is. This is akin to a tech startup marketing the hell out of a product that’s unable to retain its existing customers. The proper approach is to nail the product before trying to push it into the market.</description></item><item><title>NFL Thursdays on Twitter</title><link>/2016/09/25/nfl-thursdays-on-twitter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/09/25/nfl-thursdays-on-twitter/</guid><description>In April, Twitter announced a deal with the NFL to broadcast Thursday night games and I gave it a shot this past Thursday via the Twitter app on my FireTV. The primary motivation was to watch the game but I was also curious to see Twitter’s implementation. I was pleasantly surprised by how smooth and clean the overall experience was: you could watch the entire game without knowing it was via Twitter but the tweets added a please, yet optional, touch.</description></item><item><title>A smarter Touch ID</title><link>/2016/09/23/a-smarter-touch-id/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/09/23/a-smarter-touch-id/</guid><description>Apple’s Touch ID is great but one thing it doesn&amp;rsquo;t handle well is wet fingers. Even if my hands are a little bit sweaty or not completely dry it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to unlock the phone. Yet as soon as they’re dry the phone immediately unlocks. What’s surprising, especially given Apple&amp;rsquo;s focus on delivering the perfect user experience, is that this is still a problem. I&amp;rsquo;m not familiar with the hardware behind Touch ID but even if there&amp;rsquo;s some sort of warped fingerprint it should be good enough.</description></item><item><title>Smarter geographic ad targeting</title><link>/2016/07/26/smarter-geographic-ad-targeting/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/07/26/smarter-geographic-ad-targeting/</guid><description>Targeting is one of the best ways to improve the return on an advertising campaign. By identifying potential customers you&amp;rsquo;re able to focus your advertising on them rather than someone random. And one of the best simplest ways is to set up your advertising campaigns to focus on a specific geography. Maybe your product is only sold in the United States and advertising it elsewhere is a waste. Or maybe your product is sold everywhere but the messaging and copy needs to vary by region.</description></item><item><title>Double down on your brand and IP</title><link>/2016/07/22/double-down-on-your-brand-and-ip/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/07/22/double-down-on-your-brand-and-ip/</guid><description>Pokemon Go is huge right now. People across all age ranges, demographics, and geographies are getting involved and it’s hard to imagine this sort of adoption for any other game. What I find fascinating is that Pokemon Go was based on the same augmented reality mechanics as Ingress, another game developed by Niantic Labs. Ingress has a loyal following but pales in comparison against Pokemon Go when looking at the user numbers, despite Pokemon Go being less than 2 weeks old while Ingress has been around for almost 4 years.</description></item><item><title>Whatever happened to automatic login?</title><link>/2016/07/16/whatever-happened-to-automatic-login/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/07/16/whatever-happened-to-automatic-login/</guid><description>When I started building sites one of the accepted principles was to give customers what they want as soon as you can. This manifested itself by taking users to the logged in view whenever they navigated to the site’s homepage. This makes sense - if you know a user’s logged in why waste their time by showing them a homepage that’s designed to sell the product?
Yet recently I encountered two sites, Greenhouse and Tallie, that will default to the homepage and only load the logged in view when I click the sign in link.</description></item><item><title>A Twitter Moments fail</title><link>/2016/07/10/a-twitter-moments-fail/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/07/10/a-twitter-moments-fail/</guid><description>I’m a huge Twitter fan so it’s especially frustrating when I encounter issues. The latest one was discovering a &amp;ldquo;This content is not available in your country&amp;rdquo; message when trying to catch up on some Euro Cup highlights in a moment. I understand that in today’s digital rights world there’s always a chance for some content to be unavailable but there’s no reason it should have been included in Twitter’s flagship product that’s supposed to attract and engage new users.</description></item><item><title>Snapchat's massive potential</title><link>/2016/07/03/snapchats-massive-potential/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/07/03/snapchats-massive-potential/</guid><description>The more I use Snapchat the more obvious the potential. The way the product has evolved reminds me of Facebook’s history. Facebook started simply as a profile page for Ivy League college students but due to strong execution and brilliant product decisions has grown into the current behemoth. Snapchat is on a similar path - the initial version was a simple ephemeral photo sharing app but the recent updates seem frequent and massively impactful.</description></item><item><title>Low cost at small scale</title><link>/2016/06/26/low-cost-at-small-scale/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/06/26/low-cost-at-small-scale/</guid><description>The Wall Street Journal had a great piece on why produce is so cheap in Chinatown. The conclusion:
Her discovery: Chinatown’s 80-plus produce markets are cheap because they are connected to a web of small farms and wholesalers that operate independently of the network supplying most mainstream supermarkets.
Most of the city’s fruits and vegetables come from wholesalers at the Hunts Point Produce Market, the South Bronx distribution hub boasting all the color and accessibility of La Guardia Airport.</description></item><item><title>The Brave browser</title><link>/2016/06/23/the-brave-browser/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/06/23/the-brave-browser/</guid><description>Trying to launch a new browser seems like a fool’s errand and yet if there’s anyone that can do it it’s Brendan Eich, who in addition to creating JavaScript also ran Mozilla. Given his pedigree I decided to give his new browser, Brave, a shot. It’s definitely a bit on the rough side compared to the mainstream browsers but it’s surprisingly fast. The speed improvement comes from a built in adblocker rather than having it implemented via slower browser extensions.</description></item><item><title>Messaging app fragmentation</title><link>/2016/06/22/messaging-app-fragmentation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/06/22/messaging-app-fragmentation/</guid><description>The messaging space is fascinating. There are probably hundreds of apps available with pretty massive fragmentation. Onavo collected the following data to indicate the reach of the various messaging apps by country and while WhatsApp (owned by Facebook) is clearly dominant there are some countries that WhatsApp is a fringe player, especially among Asian countries.
via TechCrunch
It’s shocking how dominant the local companies are in Asia. WeChat is the behemoth in China.</description></item><item><title>AWS, Stripe, and WeWork</title><link>/2016/06/18/aws-stripe-and-wework/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/06/18/aws-stripe-and-wework/</guid><description>I have been subscribed to Stratechery for almost a year now but have recently started listening to the Exponent podcasts. One of them, titled Pickaxe Retailers, makes the case that WeWork has an appropriate valuation due to their ability to leverage their strong brand and become the utility layer for real estate as well as provide a slew of products to their tenants. Similar to the way AWS has eliminated the need to run your own data center and Stripe has eliminated the need to acquire merchant accounts and negotiate with vendors, WeWork may do the same for physical space - both commercial and residential.</description></item><item><title>Irrationality of the markets: Amazon up, Netflix down</title><link>/2016/04/18/irrationality-of-the-markets-amazon-up-netflix-down/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/04/18/irrationality-of-the-markets-amazon-up-netflix-down/</guid><description>Last night, Amazon announced that in addition to the annual plan they’re going to start offering Prime as a monthly service. Sure enough, investors interpreted this as good move by Amazon (up 1.51% at end of day) while hurting Netflix (down 2.79% at end of day and even more post earnings). These percentages translate into a $1.34B decrease to the Netflix valuation and a $4.49B increase in valuation for Amazon. As a shareholder of both I find this behavior interesting for its irrationality.</description></item><item><title>The corporate email signup design pattern</title><link>/2016/04/13/the-corporate-email-signup-design-pattern/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/04/13/the-corporate-email-signup-design-pattern/</guid><description>One of the latest trends I’ve noticed is B2B companies is allowing you to sign up with a company email address and automatically linking you with the rest of the organization. This is a definite no-brainer and a really simple way of getting new users setup without having to be bottlenecked by a burdensome administrative process. No one on the HR team has to enter employees into the system nor send anyone their username or account info.</description></item><item><title>Ben Thompson's “laddering up” and building bigger moats</title><link>/2016/04/03/ben-thompsons-laddering-up-and-building-bigger-moats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/04/03/ben-thompsons-laddering-up-and-building-bigger-moats/</guid><description>Last weekend I finished the The Everything Store, which details the rise of Amazon from a fledgling online book retailer to its current form. One pattern that stood out for me was how Amazon was able to continuously push into new business areas due to the infrastructure that they had in place based on previous decisions and commitments.
They started with books but were able to grow into other smaller products once they figured out the logistics behind shipping smaller items.</description></item><item><title>Airbnb, Uber, and local laws</title><link>/2016/03/06/airbnb-uber-and-local-laws/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/03/06/airbnb-uber-and-local-laws/</guid><description>Yesterday I read an interesting piece on Airbnb in New Orleans. The content itself isn&amp;rsquo;t new - it highlights the typical conflict between those that view Airbnb as violating local ordinances and ruining the city and others who believe that Airbnb brings value and is helping New Orleans rebuild after Katrina.
But what was interesting was the repeated claims of Airbnb and the other rental marketplaces that it’s just not scalable to follow local policies for every city and it’s up to the users to know their local regulations and follow them.</description></item><item><title>Don't build a Homer</title><link>/2016/02/07/dont-build-a-homer/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/02/07/dont-build-a-homer/</guid><description>Years ago, one of my projects at Yodle involved building out an automated reporting system that would consolidate all the existing reports being run via SQL queries and consolidate them into a unified application that would take care of the execution and the delivery. During the design process I spoke with existing users to see what else they’d like and it quickly morphed from a cron-job like application that just emailed CSV files based on SQL queries into a full fledged business intelligence tool that users could use to pull arbitrary data formatted in a multitude of ways.</description></item><item><title>Know what's mission critical</title><link>/2015/12/15/know-whats-mission-critical/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/12/15/know-whats-mission-critical/</guid><description>The accepted belief is that startups should move quickly and err on the side of speed rather than quality. This makes sense. Startups are so risky that they won’t fail due to making a few mistakes but will fail if they get out maneuvered and out innovated. The big advantage startups have is speed and that needs be leveraged.
The one caveat I’d make is that every company, big and small, should have mission critical elements that need to be maintained when pushing new features and updates.</description></item><item><title>Why are Netflix and Spotify so different?</title><link>/2015/11/22/why-are-netflix-and-spotify-so-different/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/11/22/why-are-netflix-and-spotify-so-different/</guid><description>The news that Adele was not going to put her new album on the streaming services got me thinking about the differences between the way music and video are consumed. Just last week Rdio announced that it’s selling its assets to Pandora which is a reminder of how hard it is to start a music company - music labels wield all the control and are able to dictate the terms they want.</description></item><item><title>Internalizing externalities</title><link>/2015/09/15/internalizing-externalities/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/09/15/internalizing-externalities/</guid><description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve adopted the practice of having the engineering team support other team when the core technology can support it - even if hasn&amp;rsquo;t been fully built in to the product. This may require manually adding entries to a series of database tables that or manually pulling reports that aren&amp;rsquo;t yet availabe via the UI. Despite being an inefficiency for the engineering team it provides a variety of benefits that outweigh this minor inconvenience.</description></item><item><title>Workaround driven product development</title><link>/2015/09/13/workaround-driven-product-development/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/09/13/workaround-driven-product-development/</guid><description>As engineers, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to get focused on technical problems and lose sight of the business. We realize our code will be used externally but we have a tendency to focus on what&amp;rsquo;s close to home rather than the actual real world usage. One of the biggest eye openers for me has been seeing people interact with our products.
We like to think of ourselves as &amp;ldquo;hackers&amp;rdquo; but it&amp;rsquo;s amazing to see the length people go to &amp;ldquo;hack&amp;rdquo; our products to do what they want.</description></item><item><title>Smart OSes</title><link>/2015/09/05/smart-oses/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/09/05/smart-oses/</guid><description>It feels as if Google has been getting better and better at what I call search inference. I’ll oftentimes do a search for a particular place on either Google Maps or the general site and see it automatically show up in Google Now. Or I will start with a simple search query that needs to be refined with Google able to offer perfect suggestions. Given how much data they’re collecting it’s not a surprise but it’s an easy way to realize I’m not that unique.</description></item><item><title>Come on Twitter</title><link>/2015/09/03/come-on-twitter/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/09/03/come-on-twitter/</guid><description>Eugene Wei published a great post on the power of networks and how Twitter hasn’t been taking advantage of their core product - a public messaging protocol. Given this thesis, Twitter should move away from the artificial 140 character limit and innovate on top of the protocol rather than be bound by it.
I’m not nearly as eloquent but I also have my gripes with Twitter that his post motivated me to write.</description></item><item><title>Properly handling text based two factor authentication</title><link>/2015/06/20/properly-handling-text-based-two-factor-authentication/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/06/20/properly-handling-text-based-two-factor-authentication/</guid><description>The purpose of two factor authentication is to prevent unauthorized access to your accounts by requiring a device other than a password to verify that it’s actually you. Usually this is a text message to a phone or an app such as Authy or Google Authenticator. Being paranoid and despite the inconvenience I chose to do it for the vast majority of my accounts that support it but some are significantly more secure than others.</description></item><item><title>The Edmunds API</title><link>/2015/06/19/the-edmunds-api/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/06/19/the-edmunds-api/</guid><description>As part of the RelayRides analysis I needed to estimate the price of a car and stumbled across the Edmunds API. I came in with some low expectations but was pleasantly surprised by how well it worked. I thought I’d need to go through a data cleanup process to make sure I was using the correct arguments in the HTTP requests but somewhat remarkably the Edmunds API was able to properly handle nearly every request.</description></item><item><title>The uncanny valley of advertising</title><link>/2015/04/12/the-uncanny-valley-of-advertising/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/04/12/the-uncanny-valley-of-advertising/</guid><description>Old Spice ad mocking the uncanny valley (Credit: Gizmodo)
The uncanny valley is this idea that although we keep getting better at depicting people through technology, a few small kinks ruin everything and make people feel repulsed compared to an obvious imitation. Another way to explain it is that we’re a lot more comfortable with cartoon characters that are obviously fake than pseudo-realistic video game characters that look real but have non-human behavior or expressions.</description></item><item><title>iOS first and username claiming</title><link>/2015/03/29/ios-first-and-username-claiming/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/03/29/ios-first-and-username-claiming/</guid><description>Both Meerkat and Periscope launched on iOS first. That doesn’t bother me despite have an Android phone. They’re running a business and it’s up to them to decide where they want to invest the time they have. What bothers me is that I’ve been using a specific username across the various services, dangoldin, and now run the risk of losing it on these newer networks. A simple fix would be to at least allow me to preregister my username without requiring an iOS device.</description></item><item><title>Why login after resetting your password?</title><link>/2015/03/24/why-login-after-resetting-your-password/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/03/24/why-login-after-resetting-your-password/</guid><description>I can’t figure out why nearly every website forces you to login after resetting your password. It’s an extra step that adds nothing to security and introduces friction into the experience. The fact that I just entered my password into a form field should be enough to trigger the authentication flow and get me back into the app. The only reasons I can think of that it’s a way to confirm that the person actually remembers their new password or that the functionality just hasn’t been built.</description></item><item><title>Introducing jsonify.me</title><link>/2015/01/04/introducing-jsonify.me/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/01/04/introducing-jsonify.me/</guid><description>Over the past few weeks I’ve been experimenting with Node.js and wanted to share the project I’ve been working on, jsonify.me. It’s an “API only” product without an interface other than a documentation page. The idea is to allow anyone to have a publicly accessible URL endpoint that can contain whatever information they want as long as it can be stored as a JSON object. In my case, I have all sorts of semi-structured data that I want to make accessible and keeping it under my domain (json.</description></item><item><title>Amazon's Fire TV Stick</title><link>/2014/12/18/amazons-fire-tv-stick/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/12/18/amazons-fire-tv-stick/</guid><description>Photo by Rancho de la Luna
Earlier this week I set up Amazon’s Fire TV Stick and wanted to jot down some thoughts while they’re still fresh. For the $20 promotion price, it’s a great deal. My alternative was an Xbox 360 along with a Raspberry Pi running XBMC. The Xbox would be used for streaming shows on Netflix and watching older DVDs while the Raspberry Pi would let me watch various files off of a USB stick.</description></item><item><title>AWS: Always shipping</title><link>/2014/11/24/aws-always-shipping/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/11/24/aws-always-shipping/</guid><description>I never thought about this until Shaun brought it up but now I see it all the time: AWS ships code quicker than any other company that size. Some are simple feature improvements to existing products, such as an advanced instance search, additional configuration options for ELBs, and new instance types, but others are entirely new products, such as Lambda, EC2 Container Service, and the newly announced code management suite.</description></item><item><title>Paying publishers without ads</title><link>/2014/11/20/paying-publishers-without-ads/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/11/20/paying-publishers-without-ads/</guid><description>Google recently launched a program, Contributor, that offers an ad-free monetization model to publishers. The idea is that a user pays Google up to $3 a month and in return Google will not show that user any display ads on a website that’s a participant in the program. The monthly payment will then be distributed across the participating sites - most likely based on how many times you’ve visited that site.</description></item><item><title>Luxury for cheap</title><link>/2014/11/05/luxury-for-cheap/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/11/05/luxury-for-cheap/</guid><description>I recently read a FiveThirtyEight article on the sneaker resale market. The concept is extremely foreign to me since I tend to not collect anything other than old notes and have a tendency of grossly mistreating my shoes and clothes. Nonetheless, I found it fascinating as it discusses the incentives of the various parties involved and comparing them against standard economic theory. One passage in particular was so insightful that I had to save it:</description></item><item><title>Tools as tools, not products</title><link>/2014/11/01/tools-as-tools-not-products/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/11/01/tools-as-tools-not-products/</guid><description>I keep on discovering new use cases for Markdown the more I use it. My first exposure was when I migrated my blog to GitHub pages from Wordpress and Tumblr. Since then I’ve discovered GitHub flavored markdown which supports syntax highlighting which has been amazingly useful when blogging on tech topics or putting together notes for a tech talk. Just recently I wanted to include some MySQL snippets in a Keynote presentation and discovered the Remark.</description></item><item><title>Link bait titles are a race to zero</title><link>/2014/10/18/link-bait-titles-are-a-race-to-zero/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/10/18/link-bait-titles-are-a-race-to-zero/</guid><description>A couple of days ago I saw a mic.com article with the title “A European country is now offering free college education to Americans” but the only way to find out which country this was (Germany) was by clicking through to the actual page.
I understand that content sites make the bulk of their revenue through advertising but resorting to a link-bait approach seems like a terrible idea. It’s a shortsighted attempt that increases page views at the cost of insulting your audience and cheapening your effort that will not work as a sustainable strategy.</description></item><item><title>Mobile web browsing and Javelin</title><link>/2014/09/27/mobile-web-browsing-and-javelin/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/09/27/mobile-web-browsing-and-javelin/</guid><description>Something that’s bothered me ever since I started using a smartphone is the link opening behavior. Whenever I’m in an app and click on a web link it would immediately open up that page in a browser window. And when I’m already in a mobile browser and click on a link it would open that page up in a new tab. Compare this with the desktop environment. Clicking on a link within an app does open up a new browser window immediately but since there are shortcuts to quickly switch between programs it’s not a huge deal.</description></item><item><title>Dev tools matter</title><link>/2014/09/25/dev-tools-matter/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/09/25/dev-tools-matter/</guid><description>It’s amazing the impact tools have on productivity and enjoyment. I remember my first foray into Java using a combination of text editors and Ant. Setting up and configuring a simple project was a nightmare and without the internet I don’t know how I would have figured it out. This initial experience made me associate Java with an unnecessarily complicated approach that I wanted to avoid.
After Java, Python felt like a breath of fresh air.</description></item><item><title>Curated Twitter timelines and the tech stack</title><link>/2014/09/08/curated-twitter-timelines-and-the-tech-stack/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/09/08/curated-twitter-timelines-and-the-tech-stack/</guid><description>Apparently Twitter is considering curation user’s timelines. A perspective people haven’t really discussed is the impact on the tech side. Right now each user has a unique timeline that needs to be presented in near-real time in case they need to see it. This results in a massive storage operation using Redis where these timelines are continuously generated and cached. By moving to a model where every user can be categorized into a group that sees a particular set of tweets Twitter can drastically reduce the amount of data they need to store per user.</description></item><item><title>API first startups</title><link>/2014/09/01/api-first-startups/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/09/01/api-first-startups/</guid><description>When building a SAAS product geared towards developers the quickest way to start is to build an API. One can even make the argument that the MVP should just be the API documentation. This benefits both sides. Potential users of the API will know exactly what to expect and have a clear understanding of the functionality and limitations and you can quickly see if there are any issues or inconsistencies in what you’re building.</description></item><item><title>Trick your users into staying</title><link>/2014/08/18/trick-your-users-into-staying/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/08/18/trick-your-users-into-staying/</guid><description>It’s just too easy to rant against LinkedIn but I can’t help it. They recently offered me a free month of business plus so I took them up on it. Little did I know (although I should have expected it) that canceling would be a maze that I still may not have escaped.
The cancel screen hides the downgrade to free option and automatically chooses a paid “recommended account” with a bright clickable “Downgrade Account” button.</description></item><item><title>Amazon courting app developers for the Fire phone</title><link>/2014/07/10/amazon-courting-app-developers-for-the-fire-phone/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/07/10/amazon-courting-app-developers-for-the-fire-phone/</guid><description>I’m a bit late to the Amazon Fire Phone party but wanted to chime in with a perspective I haven’t seen written about. Amazon is offering a $6 CPM to mobile app developers that launch an Amazon app during Auguster and September. Given that typical CPMs are less than a dollar with premium publishers like Facebook and Twitter getting close to $6, this is a very aggressive move by Amazon to build out their ecosystem.</description></item><item><title>On Google Now</title><link>/2014/07/09/on-google-now/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/07/09/on-google-now/</guid><description>As much as it pains me to admit it I’m really enjoying Google Now. I’m aware of how much information I&amp;rsquo;m sharing with Google to make it helpful but at the moment I find the tradeoff worth it.
It came in especially useful as I&amp;rsquo;ve been traveling over the past couple of weeks:
Show the official exchange rate when traveling. This may not be perfect, especially in the case of &amp;ldquo;blue markets,&amp;rdquo; but it&amp;rsquo;s nice having a rough idea of how much a US dollar is worth.</description></item><item><title>On Fab's latest move</title><link>/2014/05/24/on-fabs-latest-move/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/05/24/on-fabs-latest-move/</guid><description>Fab recently laid off a third of their staff as they transition from designer flash sales into customized goods and their own private label. The business is tough and reminded me of our experiences building Makers Alley. We initially set out to build a place where people can buy customized, personal furniture from local designers. The idea was was consumers would benefit from being able to get items that are custom made and can be customized to fit individual styles while supporting a local business and makers would have a new avenue to sell their products and build their brand.</description></item><item><title>Logging in through your inbox</title><link>/2014/05/20/logging-in-through-your-inbox/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/05/20/logging-in-through-your-inbox/</guid><description>MixPanel has a clever way of handling failed login attempts. Instead of locking the user out of the account or forcing a password reset they send an email with two links - one to log in to the account directly and another to reset the password. I don’t recall ever seeing this approach before and wish more sites started doing it. This approach also obviates the need to even have a password - a site can just send a “login link” for an entered email address and the user can login via their inbox.</description></item><item><title>System knowledge and human creativity</title><link>/2014/04/28/system-knowledge-and-human-creativity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/04/28/system-knowledge-and-human-creativity/</guid><description>Last week I read an interesting article about humans replacing robots in Toyota&amp;rsquo;s factory. The thesis being that only humans are creative enough (right now at least) to develop new skills and processes to deal with production inefficiencies. This rings true - in order to improve a manufacturing system you need to understand the entire process, from the raw ingredients up to the way consumers end up using the product. It&amp;rsquo;s more difficult to do these days as products become more complicated with an increasing number of specialized components and I&amp;rsquo;m glad to see companies taking a longer term view and focusing on the value of human creativity rather than short term cost cutting.</description></item><item><title>Craigslist: the web's fertilizer</title><link>/2014/04/25/craigslist-the-webs-fertilizer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/04/25/craigslist-the-webs-fertilizer/</guid><description>Craigslist has become the fertilizer of the web. This realization came to me last week when I needed to get a replacement phone and decided to search for one on Craigslist.Filtering past the obvious scams I thought I find a legitimate offer and reached out. Within a few minutes I received the following response from &amp;ldquo;Kyle&amp;rdquo;:
Hi a guy bought this from me, but I can tell you where I got it from.</description></item><item><title>Self hosted services</title><link>/2014/04/07/self-hosted-services/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/04/07/self-hosted-services/</guid><description>It never bothered me when apps were acquired and shut down but the Readmill news hit me hard. It was one of the truly “free” ebook readers and never got in my way. It fit my behavior perfectly - I would download my books from wherever, drag them into the Readmill web app, and have them permanently accessible on my iPad after a quick sync.
My first reaction was wishing that it would be open sourced but that got me thinking about third party services.</description></item><item><title>Goodbye Gmail</title><link>/2014/03/18/goodbye-gmail/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/03/18/goodbye-gmail/</guid><description>Over the course of the past year I’ve become more and more pissed off at Gmail. I loved using Gmail when it launched - it made writing and reading email a pleasure. It was simple, clean, and responsive. Now it’s the opposite. All actions feel slow. The initial page load takes a substantial amount of time and then I get to wait for the various page elements to load - including a chat list that I’m almost never signed into and integration with a slew of other Google products.</description></item><item><title>Follow the WhatsApp money</title><link>/2014/03/06/follow-the-whatsapp-money/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/03/06/follow-the-whatsapp-money/</guid><description>Earlier this week I received the following email from imo.im:
It’s amazing what $19 billion can do. For years imo.im has supported third party chat clients but within a couple of weeks of the WhatsApp acquisition they’ve abandoned that support to focus on their own network and become the next WhatsApp. For a while now they’ve been building features to support this move - videos in August, stickers in January - and I wonder what would have happened if they focused on their platform earlier.</description></item><item><title>Foursquare as a contact book</title><link>/2014/02/13/foursquare-as-a-contact-book/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/02/13/foursquare-as-a-contact-book/</guid><description>A few days ago I discovered a new use case for Foursquare when I was meeting up with a friend. We were catching up and during the course of the conversation I realized I needed to introduce him to someone I had met earlier. Unfortunately, I completely blanked on his name and company. All I recalled was that he frequently checked into his company on Foursquare. Sure enough, when I opened up Foursquare I saw that he had checked in there that morning.</description></item><item><title>Why I manage my own blog</title><link>/2014/02/02/why-i-manage-my-own-blog/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/02/02/why-i-manage-my-own-blog/</guid><description>Given the recent news of Medium raising $25M and Svbtle opening up to the public I thought it would be an appropriate time to explain why I’m not using either of them. They’re both simple, clean products that allow writers to concentrate on their writing rather than configuring the dozens of options available in other blogging platforms. They’ve also done a great job with the typography that makes the content enjoyable to read.</description></item><item><title>Emotional products</title><link>/2014/01/19/emotional-products/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/01/19/emotional-products/</guid><description>In 2013, I gave myself a goal of running 1000 miles. I used RunKeeper to record my runs and used its goal feature to track my progress and quickly see how much I had left. Two days before the new year, I was able to hit my goal and got a little notification from RunKeeper congratulating me on achieving my goal. This small notification got me thinking about how emotion is built into our products.</description></item><item><title>Ebook readers</title><link>/2014/01/15/ebook-readers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/01/15/ebook-readers/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m an avid reader and have embraced the move to digital. An internet connection gives me access to thousands of books with a device that’s thinner than a single book. What I grapple with are the reading apps - I can’t find one that does everything I want.
On my iPad, I have iBooks, Readmill, Oyster, Kindle, and ShuBook with each having a separate use case. iBooks and the Kindle app are for books that I purchased from iTunes and Amazon, respectively.</description></item><item><title>Surge pricing ideas</title><link>/2014/01/05/surge-pricing-ideas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/01/05/surge-pricing-ideas/</guid><description>Every time there’s a big event or terrible weather, there’s a slew of complaints about Uber’s surge pricing. By now, you’d think that Uber customers would expect this to happen and yet they’re surprised when a $10 cab ride turns into a $100 Uber ride. I suspect Uber’s already done as much as it can on the messaging side; psychologically it’s just tough for someone to take a $10 ride one day and then a day later pay an order of magnitude more.</description></item><item><title>Global products</title><link>/2013/12/25/global-products/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/12/25/global-products/</guid><description>The trip to India got me thinking about “global products” that work the same wherever they are. It’s surprisingly difficult to find tech products that fit this description. Cell phones will almost always work internationally but roaming charges make it impractical. Having an unlocked phone helps but you still need to get a SIM card which is a hassle in many countries.
Even something as standard as a laptop isn’t as easy to use as it should be.</description></item><item><title>CSV powered products</title><link>/2013/12/21/csv-powered-products/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/12/21/csv-powered-products/</guid><description>Something that I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about ever since I worked as a product manager focused on internal tools is being able to run a product entirely through CSV file uploads. Instead of building a UX designed to handle bulk operations and complicated workflows you build support for file uploads and handle the business logic entirely on the backend. The motivation is that it’s extremely difficult to build a UI that’s going to be as powerful and flexible as a simple CSV file, especially when outside tools, such as Excel, can help generate these files.</description></item><item><title>Why are there so many cleaning startups?</title><link>/2013/12/09/why-are-there-so-many-cleaning-startups/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/12/09/why-are-there-so-many-cleaning-startups/</guid><description>The recent rise of marketplace startups is great and benefits all except the incumbent. They provide much needed liquidity and transparency to markets that helpfully reduce costs to the consumer and increase volume to the provider.
Yet I’m surprised by the number of home cleaning service startups out there. I’m aware of HomeJoy, Exec, GetMaid, MyClean, and HandyBook, but am sure there are countless other copycats. The Uber approach works because it’s for an immediate service with a one time transaction where the value provided is somewhat of a commodity.</description></item><item><title>A Twitter flashback</title><link>/2013/11/16/a-twitter-flashback/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/11/16/a-twitter-flashback/</guid><description>I was going through my drafts and stumbled onto one that was going to criticize Twitter’s API changes that they announced last August. In light of last week’s IPO I thought I’d finally finish it up.
The blog post described the changes Twitter planned on making with the intent of taking control of the developer ecosystem. The changes included being a lot more strict with their API by limiting the number of users a client could authenticate, reducing the volume of API calls, and requiring all Twitter content to be displayed the same way.</description></item><item><title>Is Excel on a Mac intentionally hobbled?</title><link>/2013/11/09/is-excel-on-a-mac-intentionally-hobbled/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/11/09/is-excel-on-a-mac-intentionally-hobbled/</guid><description>The longer I’ve been involved in tech the fewer Windows laptops I’ve been seeing. It seems that to even be considered a startup you need to be giving your employees MacBooks. My conversion came years ago when I made the move from Linux in order to be able to run Excel since neither OpenOffice nor Google Spreadsheet were cutting it. Unfortunately, even after years of effort, I still can’t get to the same level of productivity as I had when using Windows during my consulting days.</description></item><item><title>Security in the wake of MongoHQ</title><link>/2013/11/07/security-in-the-wake-of-mongohq/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/11/07/security-in-the-wake-of-mongohq/</guid><description>Over the past few days my inbox has been filled with security alert emails caused by the MongoHQ database hack. I’m impressed by the number of customers MongoHQ was able to sign up - they spanned the gamut from sites that I don’t even recall signing up for to startups that have been getting significant buzz.
If a database as a service company is able to get hacked it doesn’t leave me optimistic about the way other companies are securing our data.</description></item><item><title>What the SEO? Followup</title><link>/2013/10/30/what-the-seo-followup/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/10/30/what-the-seo-followup/</guid><description>Last week I posted about a site my mom discovered that had copied the content from her site and has been positioning as their business. I had no clue what the motivation behind it was other than thinking it was just a sketchy way to either blackmail the real business owner or use black hat SEO tactics to increase traffic and monetize using AdSense.
After sharing my problem and getting a ton of advice, I sent a DMCA request to the host, Colocation America, and received a surprisingly quick reply.</description></item><item><title>What the SEO?</title><link>/2013/10/20/what-the-seo/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/10/20/what-the-seo/</guid><description>My mom owns a small local business in suburban NJ, The Do Re Mi School, that’s akin to an after-school program where music, dance, art, language and math is taught. Being surrounded by a family of engineers, we’ve been helping her on the tech side and my brother created the web site she’s been using it for the past couple of years. It’s based on Drupal and allows her to make changes without having to dive into the tech details.</description></item><item><title>Why's the iPhone 5C so expensive?</title><link>/2013/10/01/whys-the-iphone-5c-so-expensive/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/10/01/whys-the-iphone-5c-so-expensive/</guid><description>Many people expected the iPhone 5C to be priced low in order to compete with the cheaper Android phones in countries without carrier subsidies. The news that the 5C’s starting price was $549 left many in the tech community surprised and concerned with many believing that the price needed to be lower than $400 in order to compete worldwide.
I'm definitely speculating but I believe the reason for such a high price for the 5C was to avoid cannibalizing the sales of the 5S while also framing the comparison to be iPhone vs iPhone instead of iPhone vs Android.</description></item><item><title>Going rate for an email address</title><link>/2013/09/30/going-rate-for-an-email-address/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/09/30/going-rate-for-an-email-address/</guid><description>A couple of months ago I started noticing popups on various ecommerce sites offering a first purchase discounts in exchange for entering an email address. Every time I noticed this happening I took a screenshot to track the offer and compile a list of the retailers using this approach. I’m still collecting examples and would more of them but so far the going rate seems to be anywhere from 10 to 25% off the first order.</description></item><item><title>Pricing small consulting projects</title><link>/2013/09/28/pricing-small-consulting-projects/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/09/28/pricing-small-consulting-projects/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing some consulting work over the few months and wanted to share a pricing model that’s been working well for smaller projects. I’ll sit down with the client to understand the scope of the project and work with them to break it down into smaller, more manageable components. Based on this break down, I’ll estimate the time required for each piece and come up with an estimated total time.</description></item><item><title>Startups aren't black and white</title><link>/2013/09/02/startups-arent-black-and-white/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/09/02/startups-arent-black-and-white/</guid><description>When I was making the leap into the startup world I read every post I came across that talked about people’s experiences and guides in running a startup. The goal was to learn as much as I could form others and apply these hard-fought lessons my own startup. Now that I’ve been working on a startup for almost two years I realize how much startups differ from one another and how black and white these guides tend to be.</description></item><item><title>Netflix profiles, why now?</title><link>/2013/08/14/netflix-profiles-why-now/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/08/14/netflix-profiles-why-now/</guid><description>Netflix recently reintroduced profiles so now each household member can get their own recommendations, recently watched items, and instant queue rather than being forced to share the same polluted profile. This is an awesome win for Netflix customers but it’s been bugging me that they didn’t do this sooner; it’s such an obvious feature that it should have been built as soon as Netflix realized that multiple family members would be sharing their account.</description></item><item><title>Introducing Better 404</title><link>/2013/08/07/introducing-better-404/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/08/07/introducing-better-404/</guid><description>I don’t understand why websites try to compete on having the cleverest 404 page. The fact that someone ended up on a 404 page is a sign that something is broken but instead of trying to fix the problem they try to distract their visitors by making them laugh. It’s equivalent to getting to a restaurant and seeing an amazing menu only to discover that it’s closed.
We can’t always control which URLs our visitors will type in or click on but we can control what they see when they get there.</description></item><item><title>The power inbox</title><link>/2013/07/27/the-power-inbox/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/07/27/the-power-inbox/</guid><description>There are only a few tabs I consistently keep open all day on my computer - Gmail, Google Calendar, Hacker News, and New Relic. Out of these, Gmail is the most important with my entire day running through it. The value of having a presence in the inbox hasn&amp;rsquo;t been lost on companies and there are a ton of third party apps that make Gmail more useful - Rapportive, YesWare, ToutApp, and Boomerang.</description></item><item><title>Marketplaces are hard</title><link>/2013/07/13/marketplaces-are-hard/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/07/13/marketplaces-are-hard/</guid><description>There are countless posts discussing the business and marketing challenges when building a marketplace but I wanted to discuss the issues on the tech side. While we ran into technical challenges building Pressi they were mostly issues with scaling and dealing with the various social network APIs. With Makers Alley, we didn&amp;rsquo;t run into scaling or API issues but had to deal with a ton of functionality in order to be seen as a credible marketplace.</description></item><item><title>Externalizing externalities in brick and mortar</title><link>/2013/07/01/externalizing-externalities-in-brick-and-mortar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/07/01/externalizing-externalities-in-brick-and-mortar/</guid><description>Last week, I had a morning flight out of Laguardia Airport and being into all things tech decided to grab a coffee at a place called Biergarten since they had iPads at every seat. Turned out that the only way to order and pay was by using the provided iPad with the attached credit card reader. I had 30 minutes to kill before my flight and decided to spend it observing the interactions others had with this ordering system.</description></item><item><title>Business frameworks are actually useful</title><link>/2013/06/25/business-frameworks-are-actually-useful/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/06/25/business-frameworks-are-actually-useful/</guid><description>Tom Tunguz wrote a great post yesterday sharing the frameworks he uses to evaluate and analyze startups. For this post, I’m not interested in the content (which is great for anyone building a company) but I am interested in the concept of business frameworks and their application. When I was younger and came across a “business” framework I would dismiss it as obvious and move on. Now, I’m aware of how valuable a good framework can be.</description></item><item><title>Netflix, bundling, and the future of video</title><link>/2013/05/05/netflix-bundling-and-the-future-of-video/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/05/netflix-bundling-and-the-future-of-video/</guid><description>Something that’s been stuck in my head is the relationship between Netflix and bundling. On one hand, we’ve been wishing that cable came unbundled so we’d be able to just pay for the shows we want to watch. On the other hand, we have Netflix which is striving to let us stream every TV show and movie whenever and wherever we want. Why don’t we care that Netflix is actually a bundled product?</description></item><item><title>Follow through on that personal welcome email</title><link>/2013/05/02/follow-through-on-that-personal-welcome-email/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/02/follow-through-on-that-personal-welcome-email/</guid><description>Recently, I’ve been receiving many startups sending out “personal emails” from the CEO or cofounder around 30 minutes after signing up. The idea is to engage the new user by showing them that there’s a real person behind the service that cares and to offer any help that they may need. There’s a great article on Segment.io about this tactic as well as a few other emails that can be sent to improve retention.</description></item><item><title>Smart software; dumb hardware</title><link>/2013/04/24/smart-software-dumb-hardware/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/04/24/smart-software-dumb-hardware/</guid><description>Last week, three isolated events gave me a glimpse of how powerful mobile can be. Tech pundits have been saying that for a while now but experiencing it firsthand is definitely more convincing.
I went for a run with only my phone to keep me company. After my run was done, I wanted to grab a cup of iced coffee and realized that Starbucks gave me a free drink on my birthday.</description></item><item><title>Coke, Pepsi and Passover</title><link>/2013/04/05/coke-pepsi-and-passover/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/04/05/coke-pepsi-and-passover/</guid><description>During Passover, Coke and Pepsi sell sugar based versions of their sodas in order to stay kosher for Passover. These high fructose corn syrup (HFCS) free sodas are extremely popular and people stock up while they can. I don’t know whether this is due to the better taste, the nostalgia, or the limited supply but these sugar based versions are definitely more popular. I wonder what would happen if either Coke or Pepsi decided to go “all in” on sugar and launch a marketing campaign against HFCS based food and drinks.</description></item><item><title>Mailbox: Is the server required?</title><link>/2013/03/29/mailbox-is-the-server-required/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/29/mailbox-is-the-server-required/</guid><description>After a couple of weeks on the waiting list I finally got access to the Mailbox App. It’s a huge improvement over the standard mail app and my mobile email consumption habits have improved significantly. I’m still not at “inbox zero” but am making my way there.
I don’t know much about iOS development but one thing I’ve been wondering about is whether they could have written it to not use a remote server.</description></item><item><title>Welcoming the long, single webpage</title><link>/2013/03/26/welcoming-the-long-single-webpage/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/26/welcoming-the-long-single-webpage/</guid><description>A recent trend in website design I’ve been seeing is the long single page. My first distinct memory of seeing it is from Karma but I’ve started noticing it everywhere. It runs the gamut from non-profit causes to video game PR firms. In fact, we’re even using this approach for the Makers Alley homepage.
Surprisingly, it’s starting to make inroads on news sites as well. Whereas before news sites would have an article spread across 20 pages (looking at you Business Insider) in order to increase page views and show more ads, some news outlets are actually improving the user experience.</description></item><item><title>Makers Alley v2</title><link>/2013/03/16/makers-alley-v2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/16/makers-alley-v2/</guid><description>A brief one today.
This past week, Sandy and I have been super busy getting a new version of Makers Alley out that allows you to customize and buy furniture. We’re launching with two makers that have items for sale but we’re busy adding more. Withers &amp;amp; Grain specialize in using reclaimed wood from the 5 boroughs and do their own wood and metal work. Mark Grattan is a furniture designer who has designed a furniture collection for Makers Alley in a geometry-inspired style.</description></item><item><title>Account management madness</title><link>/2013/02/25/account-management-madness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/02/25/account-management-madness/</guid><description>Over the past year, I cofounded two startups and launched a bunch of side projects. Since they all had potential, I wanted to make each as standalone as possible and ended up with dedicated accounts for each. This meant that I had a flood of accounts for each, ranging from the various Google products to Sendgrid and AWS to Freshbooks and Quickbooks. Unsurprisingly, this turned out to be an unmanageable pain in the ass.</description></item><item><title>Vacationing with Foursquare</title><link>/2013/02/22/vacationing-with-foursquare/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/02/22/vacationing-with-foursquare/</guid><description>Last week, my wife and I took a vacation to New Orleans and it was the first time we used Foursquare to plan a trip. I asked friends for suggestions, looked at other Foursquare lists, and did some online research to create my list of 25 places that I wanted to visit while there. These places ranged from tourist magnets such as Bourbon Street and Cafe Du Monde to the more local places like Cafe Envie and Port of Call.</description></item><item><title>What do Fab and Groupon have in common?</title><link>/2013/01/15/what-do-fab-and-groupon-have-in-common/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/01/15/what-do-fab-and-groupon-have-in-common/</guid><description>Groupon has fascinated me since they’ve launched. It popularized an entirely new business model, encouraged the launch of hundreds of competitors, and was able to IPO three years after being founded. This sounds great until you look at the performance after the IPO: the stock is down 80% and it’s consistently missing the quarterly goals.
The daily deals space isn’t as profitable as it used to be and they’re trying to become a tool platform for small businesses.</description></item><item><title>Self hosted Instagram export</title><link>/2012/12/19/self-hosted-instagram-export/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/12/19/self-hosted-instagram-export/</guid><description>I just hacked together a quick app to help download Instagram photos. At first, I tried using Instaport and OpenPhoto but both of them were backed up with others trying to do the same so I decided to create my own. It&amp;rsquo;s basically a really simple python web app that allows you do a quick authentication with Instagram and then lets you downloads all your images to your hard drive.</description></item><item><title>Entrepreneurship is not a job</title><link>/2012/11/29/entrepreneurship-is-not-a-job/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/11/29/entrepreneurship-is-not-a-job/</guid><description>Let’s start with a joke: An American consultant was at a pier in a small coastal Mexican village when a small boat with just one fisherman docked. Inside the small boat were several large tuna. The American complimented the Mexican on the quality of his fish and asked how long it took to catch them. The Mexican replied "Only a little while." The consultant then asked why didn't he stay out longer and catch more fish?</description></item><item><title>Eating Yourself - Innovation &amp;amp; Cannibalization</title><link>/2012/08/12/eating-yourself-innovation-amp-cannibalization/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/08/12/eating-yourself-innovation-amp-cannibalization/</guid><description>I was rereading the HBR paper on Strategies for Two Sided Markets and came across a passage describing Apple’s mistake of trying to monetize both sides of their market, the consumers and the developers, rather than focusing on one like Microsoft did by giving away the SDK for free.
It got me thinking about Apple’s recovery. Many people credit the iPod with revitalizing Apple but I think there’s more than that.</description></item><item><title>In Defense of Yahoo</title><link>/2012/08/05/in-defense-of-yahoo/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/08/05/in-defense-of-yahoo/</guid><description>Reading recent tech coverage makes you think that each newly startup is more valuable than Yahoo. Yahoo is the 4th most visited site in the world with over 300 million users on Yahoo mail. This is a problem every startup should hope to have.
User acquisition is the most difficult task for a consumer startup. User attrition is an easier problem to solve than user acquisition. Yahoo doesn’t need to build a product that’s 10 times better than the competition, they just need to simplify and improve what they already have.</description></item><item><title>The Startup Advantage - Details, Details, Details</title><link>/2012/07/28/the-startup-advantage-details-details-details/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/07/28/the-startup-advantage-details-details-details/</guid><description>A frustration I’ve been experiencing more and more is having to reload a webpage in order to change the date range in the options. If a company expects me to keep a site open for more than a day they should make it easy for me to update the options. The big example is Google Analytics - I open up a page, choose a date range, and get to see my charts.</description></item><item><title>Race to 0 - RIM vs IE</title><link>/2012/07/10/race-to-0-rim-vs-ie/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/07/10/race-to-0-rim-vs-ie/</guid><description>I read an article earlier today about how companies are preparing for a possible demise of RIM and couldn’t help but compare RIM’s decline over only a few years compared to how long it’s taking IE to disappear.
To confirm that there is in fact a difference in behavior, we can compare the RIM share among smartphones and IE share among browsers. Turns out that they are noticeably different: IE is on a linear decline with close to 70% in Q3 2008 but around 36% in Q1 2012 while RIM starts at 16% in Q3 2008, goes up to a high of 21% in 2009 and then drops to 7% in Q1 2012.</description></item><item><title>Achieving browser autocomplete</title><link>/2012/06/07/achieving-browser-autocomplete/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/06/07/achieving-browser-autocomplete/</guid><description>Over the past few days, I’ve been thinking about habits. How do they form? How do they change? And the selfish one - how can you build a product that is habit forming? My cofunder sent me a great Nir &amp;amp; Far blog post that goes into detail about generating desire which is a great read to anyone building a consumer product.
Along these lines, I decided to be a bit introspective and see which products and sites are a part of my habit.</description></item><item><title>Selling to the enterprise? Target the consumer</title><link>/2012/05/22/selling-to-the-enterprise-target-the-consumer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/05/22/selling-to-the-enterprise-target-the-consumer/</guid><description>A trend I’ve been noticing more and more is enterprise sales being done bottoms up. The typical approach is to offer a free trials or have some sort of freemium product. Each sign up is then treated as an inbound lead that is assigned an account manager. Within two weeks of signing up for New Relic I was contacted by an account manager who helped answer my questions and helped me get New Relic set up for Glossi.</description></item><item><title>Draw Something Zyngafied</title><link>/2012/04/12/draw-something-zyngafied/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/04/12/draw-something-zyngafied/</guid><description>We’re aware of Zynga’s purchase of Draw Something and Zynga’s emphasis on analytics and metrics to drive product features and decisions. I’m a bit late to the party but I tried brainstorming to put together a Zyngafied version of Draw Something:
Favor drawings that require colors that a user does not have to encourage the user to buy new colors. Leverage the priming effect by picking words that will encourage users to spend more.</description></item><item><title>Future of Startups - Small Teams, Big Profit</title><link>/2012/04/10/future-of-startups-small-teams-big-profit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/04/10/future-of-startups-small-teams-big-profit/</guid><description>The big news today was that Facebook acquired Instagram for $1B in cash and stock. I don’t want to debate whether that was a good price but I am amazed that Instagram was able to get to over 30 million users with 13 employees, of which 3 are engineers. I see a few factors combining to make this an ideal model for the future tech startup.
Open source tools and the cloud have made starting easier than ever and a few motivated, talented people can build a marketable product over a weekend.</description></item><item><title>Where are the event recommendation startups?</title><link>/2012/03/30/where-are-the-event-recommendation-startups/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/03/30/where-are-the-event-recommendation-startups/</guid><description>A few years ago I worked on a startup with the goal of providing local event recommendations. Unfortunately, we were never able to make it work. We focused too much on building new features, didn’t simplify our product enough, didn’t have a focused vision, and didn’t spend time understanding the market. After reading Mark Hendrickson’s Plancast’s postmortem, I started thinking about the problem again and what a successful approach would look like.</description></item><item><title>Overcoming the Build Bias</title><link>/2012/03/24/overcoming-the-build-bias/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/03/24/overcoming-the-build-bias/</guid><description>An issue I’ve been trying to overcome is what I like to call the “build bias.” Whenever I’d run into a technical problem, I’d want to solve it on my own - whether it’s by writing some code or by installing and configuring various libraries and packages. I remember the time I needed to collect feedback for a website but instead of just using an off the shelf product like GetSatisfaction, I decided to create my own.</description></item><item><title>GroupOn Scheduler</title><link>/2011/12/08/groupon-scheduler/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2011/12/08/groupon-scheduler/</guid><description>I'm not surprised that someone came out with an online scheduling tool for SMBs. I am a bit surprised that it was GroupOn though. I suspect many smaller companies have tried doing it but found selling to the SMB much more difficult than they expected. Since GroupOn already has penetration in the SMB space they may find it a lot easier, especially if, as it looks, they will be offering it free to any business that runs a GroupOn promotion.</description></item><item><title>Google Giving Employees Free Adwords?</title><link>/2010/08/25/google-giving-employees-free-adwords/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2010/08/25/google-giving-employees-free-adwords/</guid><description>According to this [http://agtb.wordpress.com/2010/01/06/my-1day-adwords-account/](blog post), Gogole gives their emplo﻿yees $1 a day to advertise on Google. The intent is to give employees the perspective of an Adwords user in order to improve the product. In addition to giving employees exposure to Adwords, this also has potential to increase the competition in Adword auctions by causing bids to increase and leading to more revenue for Google. Given that Google has more than 10,000 employees worldwide this can have an effect on smaller advertisers.</description></item><item><title>Power of Twitter</title><link>/2009/03/08/power-of-twitter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2009/03/08/power-of-twitter/</guid><description>I may be a bit late to the party but I was finally able to see the power of Twitter this afternoon.
I kept on getting an "Authentication failed" message when trying to log in to AIM. A few years ago I would not know what to do except ask my friends if they were having any trouble. Right now, I went to searched for "AIM" on Twitter and discovered that other people were having the same problem.</description></item><item><title>Some thoughts on innovation</title><link>/2008/10/01/some-thoughts-on-innovation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2008/10/01/some-thoughts-on-innovation/</guid><description>I stumbled unto an article written in 1968 that tries to predict what the world of 2008 will be like. Usually, these types of predictions are completely off and tend to predict a future far more advanced than what it actually becomes.
As expected, the article had it&amp;rsquo;s exaggerations (automatic cars driving at 250 miles per hour, inter-continental rockets, average work day of 4 hours ) but what struck me the most is how accurate the predictions about computers are:</description></item><item><title>On Microsoft walking away from Yahoo</title><link>/2008/05/04/on-microsoft-walking-away-from-yahoo/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2008/05/04/on-microsoft-walking-away-from-yahoo/</guid><description>A little unexpected but I think this was the right decision for Microsoft for a couple of reasons:
Jerry Yang was doing everything in his power to prevent MS from acquiring Yahoo - what type of message does that send and how must the employees of Yahoo feel if their CEO is acting this way. In order to compete with Google, the merger must have gotten done quickly and smoothly, this would not have been the case in the case of a hostile takeover.</description></item><item><title>Why does EA want Take Two?</title><link>/2008/04/29/why-does-ea-want-take-two/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2008/04/29/why-does-ea-want-take-two/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why no one is pointing this out but it seems that as soon as EA acquires T2, the T2 folks would just leave to create a new studio. They seem independent and I doubt that they&amp;rsquo;d want to work for EA. And although EA would get the rights to all of the T2 games and may try to develop the series, they might not have the imagination or the guys to do it.</description></item><item><title>On Apple buying PA Semiconductor</title><link>/2008/04/25/on-apple-buying-pa-semiconductor/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2008/04/25/on-apple-buying-pa-semiconductor/</guid><description>This post is a response to Robert Cringely&amp;rsquo;s PBS Post. He&amp;rsquo;s giving 2 reasons for the acquisition and I wanted to add to two of his points.
&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;The short term reason is to force Intel to give Apple price cuts for fear that Apple will make their own chips: I do not think that Intel needs to worry about Apple manufacturing their own PC chips as Apple already went through that phase and AMD already provides the necessary pressure on Intel to lower their prices.</description></item></channel></rss>