<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>design on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/design/</link><description>Recent content in design on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What do airlines and LinkedIn have in common?</title><link>/2019/08/22/what-do-airlines-and-linkedin-have-in-common/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/08/22/what-do-airlines-and-linkedin-have-in-common/</guid><description>Supposedly airlines could make the economy seats much better than they are without a significant investment but purposefully do not in order to encourage people that can afford business or first class to choose business or first class. Perversely, this makes sense. If economy is only slightly worse than business then I&amp;rsquo;d be willing to save quite a bit of money by choosing economy for a worse experience. Yet if the economy seats were significantly worse then I&amp;rsquo;d pay a premium for business.</description></item><item><title>Combine registration and sign in</title><link>/2019/07/02/combine-registration-and-sign-in/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/07/02/combine-registration-and-sign-in/</guid><description>The goal of nearly every site or app is to get users to engage as quickly as possible. That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s surprising that so many sites have a separate flow for registration versus sign in. There&amp;rsquo;s no good reason that these two flows shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be combined.
A part of nearly every registration is entering an email and password so why not make them the first step of the sign up process?</description></item><item><title>LinkedIn's terrible messaging experience</title><link>/2019/03/10/linkedins-terrible-messaging-experience/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/03/10/linkedins-terrible-messaging-experience/</guid><description>This is a bit of a ranty post but it’s incredible how poor the LinkedIn messaging experience is. If anyone sends me a LinkedIn message I get an email telling me that so-and-so sent me a message. To read the actual message I need to clickthrough to get to the LinkedIn site. I get it, they want to increase engagement and have me access the site and show me something new.</description></item><item><title>Amazon's "Add to list" design</title><link>/2018/12/27/amazons-add-to-list-design/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/12/27/amazons-add-to-list-design/</guid><description>I use Amazon’s wish list as a placeholder of books I plan on buying. I’m not sure why I don’t just buy them immediately but whenever I’m done with a book I go to my wish list and purchase a new one. Earlier today while adding two books to my wish list I noticed something odd: the location of the “Add to list” button was different from one page to the next.</description></item><item><title>A UX gem in Google Slides</title><link>/2018/11/13/a-ux-gem-in-google-slides/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/11/13/a-ux-gem-in-google-slides/</guid><description>I’m a sucker for subtle UX gems and Google continues to amaze me. While working on a presentation using the Slides product I had to modify the colors of a few objects. The UX for this is usually pretty normal - you select the object, hit the icon to modify the color, and choose a new color. Usually it’s slightly better and you get to see the existing color. What surprised me with the Google Slides experience is that I didn’t just see the existing color but also saw the previously picked color.</description></item><item><title>Design anti pattern: Tab switching autosave</title><link>/2018/01/23/design-anti-pattern-tab-switching-autosave/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2018/01/23/design-anti-pattern-tab-switching-autosave/</guid><description>Every once in awhile I get frustrated by a product experience and turn it into a design anti pattern rant. This time it was updating a bit of information in JIRA, switching to a different tab to look something up, and then going back to realize that my change was saved. Sure it was simple to edit and update the field but it seems the field should have just stayed in edit-mode until I was explicitly done.</description></item><item><title>A Google Docs efficiency win</title><link>/2017/07/24/a-google-docs-efficiency-win/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/07/24/a-google-docs-efficiency-win/</guid><description>Old Google Docs behavior
I’m an efficiency fiend and love seeing my heavily used products updated with any and all functionality that make them a tad easier to use. A few weeks ago, Google Docs, one of my most heavily used applications - in fact where I’m writing this very post - made a minor change to the “Move to” functionality that created one of these small efficiency wins. Before the change, clicking the small folder icon while in a document would show a menu with the item’s current location and a “Move this item” option.</description></item><item><title>Slack's channel exit anti pattern</title><link>/2017/04/02/slacks-channel-exit-anti-pattern/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/04/02/slacks-channel-exit-anti-pattern/</guid><description>Slack has grown incredibly quickly and solves a difficult problem but I can’t help but notice that some design antipatterns that increase Slack usage but don’t benefit the user. I came across one of these designs on Friday when I saw someone leave a channel. They no longer found the channel useful or were only there to answer a few questions but as soon as they left everyone in the channel saw the message “so and so has left the channel.</description></item><item><title>Expiration date selection design anti pattern</title><link>/2016/05/14/expiration-date-selection-design-anti-pattern/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/05/14/expiration-date-selection-design-anti-pattern/</guid><description>Wanting to avoid a busy lunch rush but hankering for Chipotle I decided to download their app to order ahead. It’s a straightforward app and everything went as expected until I had to enter the expiration date for my credit card. The way the app is set up is that you’re expected to choose the month first followed by the year. Unfortunately it prevents you from picking a month in the past.</description></item><item><title>The corporate email signup design pattern</title><link>/2016/04/13/the-corporate-email-signup-design-pattern/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2016/04/13/the-corporate-email-signup-design-pattern/</guid><description>One of the latest trends I’ve noticed is B2B companies is allowing you to sign up with a company email address and automatically linking you with the rest of the organization. This is a definite no-brainer and a really simple way of getting new users setup without having to be bottlenecked by a burdensome administrative process. No one on the HR team has to enter employees into the system nor send anyone their username or account info.</description></item><item><title>Why login after resetting your password?</title><link>/2015/03/24/why-login-after-resetting-your-password/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/03/24/why-login-after-resetting-your-password/</guid><description>I can’t figure out why nearly every website forces you to login after resetting your password. It’s an extra step that adds nothing to security and introduces friction into the experience. The fact that I just entered my password into a form field should be enough to trigger the authentication flow and get me back into the app. The only reasons I can think of that it’s a way to confirm that the person actually remembers their new password or that the functionality just hasn’t been built.</description></item><item><title>Why log me out?</title><link>/2014/12/16/why-log-me-out/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/12/16/why-log-me-out/</guid><description>Now that fantasy football season is over for me and I have no risk of angering the fantasy football gods I can complain about an interface decision in the Yahoo Fantasy Football Android app. Every once in a while the app will sign me out, which I suspect is a security feature, but I can log back in without having to re-enter a password. The only effect this “feature” has is getting me annoyed.</description></item><item><title>An eBay design rant: timezone support</title><link>/2014/06/12/an-ebay-design-rant-timezone-support/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/06/12/an-ebay-design-rant-timezone-support/</guid><description>I recently needed to sell something on eBay and encountered an issue I thought they would have taken care of by now. Apparently you can pick the start time for an auction but it has to be in PDT - there’s no way to choose another time zone. The change is trivial and one would think that a $60B company would be able to support multiple time zones in their core product.</description></item><item><title>Logging in through your inbox</title><link>/2014/05/20/logging-in-through-your-inbox/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/05/20/logging-in-through-your-inbox/</guid><description>MixPanel has a clever way of handling failed login attempts. Instead of locking the user out of the account or forcing a password reset they send an email with two links - one to log in to the account directly and another to reset the password. I don’t recall ever seeing this approach before and wish more sites started doing it. This approach also obviates the need to even have a password - a site can just send a “login link” for an entered email address and the user can login via their inbox.</description></item><item><title>Why Bank of America, why?</title><link>/2013/12/20/why-bank-of-america-why/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/12/20/why-bank-of-america-why/</guid><description>Before leaving for a trip to India, I wanted to make sure that I’d be allowed to access the ATM so I decided to contact my bank. Surprisingly, Bank of America was modern enough to allow me to do this online. Unsurprisingly, the UX was lacking.
Instead of just asking which country I was traveling to using a simple autocomplete or dropdown they have a three step process. First, I get to choose whether I’m traveling domestic or international.</description></item><item><title>Some more design ranting</title><link>/2013/10/23/some-more-design-ranting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/10/23/some-more-design-ranting/</guid><description>I don’t know why, but I’ve become more aware of the UI/UX of various sites and apps that I encounter. Whereas before I might have gotten frustrated about some behavior, I’m now starting to get annoyed whenever I encounter something that’s obviously crummy. Here’s a few of the more recent design anti-patterns I’ve been noticing.
Submitting a login form with the wrong password removes the entered email address. Especially on mobile, where it both takes longer to type and typos are more common, it’s crappy having to type both my email and password again if I made a simple typo in my password or just don’t know which of my passwords I used.</description></item><item><title>Design anti pattern: footer under infinite scroll</title><link>/2013/09/03/design-anti-pattern-footer-under-infinite-scroll/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/09/03/design-anti-pattern-footer-under-infinite-scroll/</guid><description>I’m not sure why this needs to be said but if your site offers infinite scroll make sure you don’t have anything clickable in the footer. I’d expect the occasional site to succumb to this but I was surprised to see it happening on LinkedIn. All I wanted to do was read the developer docs but unfortunately the link is located in the footer which provides a nice challenge of clicking the link before new content is loaded.</description></item><item><title>Simplicity vs power in product design</title><link>/2013/08/28/simplicity-vs-power-in-product-design/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/08/28/simplicity-vs-power-in-product-design/</guid><description>Although I come from a backend background, I’ve been spending more and more time on the UX side of things and have been picking up quite a bit - a combination of using Twitter Bootstrap on my projects, subscribing to the Hack Design lectures, and following a ton of designers on Twitter.
Something that’s been bothering me is this obsession with trying to make every product as intuitive and approachable as possible.</description></item><item><title>Rise of flat design</title><link>/2013/08/11/rise-of-flat-design/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/08/11/rise-of-flat-design/</guid><description>I don’t know whether it’s due to the upcoming version of iOS or Windows 8 but it feels as if flat design is getting more and more common. In the past couple of weeks, I’ve noticed two “mainstream” sites, Thesaurus.com and Optimum, adopt a flat design which I suspect is the first design change they’ve made in years. Many companies are updating their iOS apps in time for the fall release and I understand the motivation to want to fit the style but it’s interesting to see websites doing the same.</description></item><item><title>A design that's too good?</title><link>/2013/07/03/a-design-thats-too-good/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/07/03/a-design-thats-too-good/</guid><description>This is a bit of a first-world problem but it’s possible for a design to be too good. A great design may lead to an increase in your vanity metrics but that won’t necessarily translate into a successful business. In fact, it’s likely that these low-value users will increase your costs.
When we redesigned the landing page for Pressi (formerly Glossi) we saw the signup rate from our landing page shoot up to to close to 34% from below 5%.</description></item><item><title>Save my reading spot, damn it</title><link>/2013/05/22/save-my-reading-spot-damn-it/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/22/save-my-reading-spot-damn-it/</guid><description>When reading a long form piece, I favor the single-page view. Unfortunately, I usually don’t find out that it’s longer than a page until I’ve finished the first page. At that point, I switch to the single page view which causes the entire page to reload and I have to skim the page to find the spot where I stopped reading.
Why haven’t any of the major content sites dealt with this yet?</description></item><item><title>The new Gmail compose</title><link>/2013/04/02/the-new-gmail-compose/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/04/02/the-new-gmail-compose/</guid><description>A few days ago, Google made the new compose default on Gmail. It went from a separate page to a popup that’s accessible from anywhere in Gmail. And for the vast majority of the time, it’s better: it’s quicker to get to and makes it easy to reference other emails while writing a new one. Unfortunately, for attaching an image (not embedding it inline) or doing some heavy formatting, it’s a huge step backwards and makes me want the old compose back.</description></item><item><title>Welcoming the long, single webpage</title><link>/2013/03/26/welcoming-the-long-single-webpage/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/26/welcoming-the-long-single-webpage/</guid><description>A recent trend in website design I’ve been seeing is the long single page. My first distinct memory of seeing it is from Karma but I’ve started noticing it everywhere. It runs the gamut from non-profit causes to video game PR firms. In fact, we’re even using this approach for the Makers Alley homepage.
Surprisingly, it’s starting to make inroads on news sites as well. Whereas before news sites would have an article spread across 20 pages (looking at you Business Insider) in order to increase page views and show more ads, some news outlets are actually improving the user experience.</description></item><item><title>App Store, what took so long?</title><link>/2013/03/01/app-store-what-took-so-long/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/01/app-store-what-took-so-long/</guid><description>In old versions of the iOS App Store, every time you downloaded a new app it would close the App Store and navigate to the screen with the now-downloading app. Recent versions of the App Store keep it open and force you explicitly exit. I’m surprised that the App Store didn’t launch with the new behavior - it must have been a conscious decision since the development effort for both seems similar.</description></item><item><title>Improving the Subway User Experience</title><link>/2012/01/12/improving-the-subway-user-experience/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/01/12/improving-the-subway-user-experience/</guid><description>Source: inhabitat.com
The combination of taking the subway every day and reading design books had me thinking of ways to improve the subway user experience, other than the obvious one of making it cleaner.
One thing that struck me is the feeling you get when you see the train leaving the station. It&amp;#8217;s annoyingly stressful and makes me wonder how long I have to wait until the next train comes. Anything that can avoid this outcome would make waiting for the train a better experience.</description></item></channel></rss>