<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>history on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/history/</link><description>Recent content in history on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>AWS Snowcone and my first job</title><link>/2020/06/19/aws-snowcone-and-my-first-job/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/06/19/aws-snowcone-and-my-first-job/</guid><description>AIT Tapes on Wikipedia
AWS recently launched Snowcone and it immediately reminded me of my first post-college job. I was a &amp;ldquo;Business Information Specialist&amp;rdquo; at ZS Associates, a consulting company with a strong emphasis on leveraging data to support pharmaceutical companies. The industry was setup in such a way that there were these massive vendors that would aggregate pharmaceutical prescription data from pharmacies, trace them to the prescriber (ie doctor), and then sell these back to the pharmaceutical companies.</description></item><item><title>A brief history of manufacturing</title><link>/2013/08/02/a-brief-history-of-manufacturing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/08/02/a-brief-history-of-manufacturing/</guid><description>Working on Makers Alley, I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a fair amount thinking about the evolution of manufacturing and wanted to share an extremely condensed history.
For most of human history, people either made what they needed on their own or traded with a local craftsman. Over time, this led to a specialization in skills and also the rise of the apprenticeship model. Since trade was mostly local, it was difficult to build a large business and most businesses were family run with parents passing down skills to their children.</description></item><item><title>Why don't cell phones have a dialtone?</title><link>/2013/04/12/why-dont-cell-phones-have-a-dialtone/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/04/12/why-dont-cell-phones-have-a-dialtone/</guid><description>While reading The Idea Factory, I came across an interesting passage that explained why cell phones don’t have dialtones:
Meanwhile, Phil Porter, who had worked with [Richard] Frenkiel on the original system, came up with a permanent answer to an interesting question. Should a cellular phone have a dial tone? Porter made a radical suggestion that it shouldn’t. A caller should dial a number and then push “send.” That way, the mobile caller would be less rushed; also, the call would be connected for a shorter time, thus putting less strain on the network.</description></item></channel></rss>