<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Running on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/running/</link><description>Recent content in Running on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/running/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why I run</title><link>/2013/11/03/why-i-run/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/11/03/why-i-run/</guid><description>&lt;p>In honor of today’s NYC marathon, I finally finished up this post that’s been sitting in my drafts folder the past few weeks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’ve never been into running until the beginning of this year when I decided to run 1000 miles. This led to me to three half marathons and is actually making me consider doing a full one. It’s amazing where a habit and a bit of effort can take you. Initially, I ran just to hit my goal and only signed up for races in order to keep myself motivated and on track. Now, it’s become significantly more than that. There are so many things outside my control yet running is solely about my effort and willpower. If I fail it’s my defeat and if I succeed it’s my victory. I can easily skip a run on a cold, rainy morning and yet I know I’m just deceiving myself and I’ll have to make it up later. Running is one of the simplest things to do and that’s a huge appeal. The human bodies have evolved to run and kids start running as soon as they learn to walk. As our world becomes increasingly complex it’s nice being able to escape with a quick run. Whether it’s running or something else, it’s important to have an outlet that rewards us based on our efforts. The further away this activity is from our day jobs the better.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My running progress</title><link>/2013/10/13/my-running-progress/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/10/13/my-running-progress/</guid><description>&lt;img src="/image/runkeeper-goal-2013.png" alt="My Running Goal" data-width="669" data-height="316" data-layout="responsive" />
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not entirely sure why, but I started off 2013 with the goal of running 1000 miles which breaks down into a little more than 19 miles a week. Remarkably, I stuck with it and am somehow at 822 miles for the year and need to average 16/week for the remainder of 2013 to hit the goal. Yet it took me a surprisingly long time to work up to a weekly distance of 19 miles and even longer to consistently run more than 19 miles a week. My first run was less than 1.5 miles and I only started consistently eat into my deficit in June. It took me until the end of August to actually reach the 19 mile cumulative weekly average I need to maintain until the end of the year. It’s been an awesome adventure and I’ve even managed to run three half marathons and improved my time from 1:58:11 on an easy course to 1:56:11 on a challenging one. Here’s a table I put together showcasing my running progress over the course of the year. I’ll update it at the end of the year after hopefully achieving the 1000 mile goal.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>