<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Math on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/math/</link><description>Recent content in Math on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/math/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Quick math calculations</title><link>/2020/01/10/quick-math-calculations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/01/10/quick-math-calculations/</guid><description>&lt;amp-twitter width="609" height="274" layout="responsive" data-tweetid="1222729308935991298">
&lt;/amp-twitter>
&lt;p>I came across a tweet earlier today that received a surprisingly large reaction for a relatively simple math shortcut: &amp;ldquo;Percentages are reversible. 8% of 25 is the as 25% of 8 and one of them is much easier to do in your head.&amp;rdquo; I followed it up with one of my own: &amp;ldquo;Similar one is use factors of 10. Want to divide by 5? Multiply by 2 and shift decimal point. 24/5=24*2/10=4.8 same with 4 and 25., 8 and 125, etc&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Math is incredible</title><link>/2017/02/19/math-is-incredible/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/02/19/math-is-incredible/</guid><description>&lt;p>Maybe I never learned this or maybe I forgot but while reading &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Prime-Obsession-Bernhard-Greatest-Mathematics/dp/0452285259">Prime Obsession&lt;/a> I came across a concept that blew my mind. We all learn about infinite series and how some converge (think 1 + ½ + ¼ + .. = 2) and some diverge (1 + ½ + ⅓ + ¼ + ..) but it turns out that not all convergent series are the same. The same numbers, added in a different order, can lead to a different resulting sum. These series are called &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/ConditionalConvergence.html">conditionally convergent&lt;/a>. This is incredible since I always assumed that addition was commutative but it turns out even fundamental ideas are violated when dealing with infinite sums. I still can’t wrap my mind around how this makes any sense but the math doesn’t lie. The example below is from the book but I’d love to see others so I can continue wrapping my head around it. I’ve been out of school for a while now but this discovery brings me back.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>