<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pricing on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/pricing/</link><description>Recent content in pricing on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/pricing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Advertising an Airbnb on Instagram</title><link>/2019/12/31/advertising-an-airbnb-on-instagram/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2019/12/31/advertising-an-airbnb-on-instagram/</guid><description>I saw an ad for a specific Airbnb on Instagram and just don&amp;rsquo;t understand the economics. It seems unlikely that running this sort of campaign ends up being profitable. I&amp;rsquo;d expect the overlap between the audience targeted and those interested in booking the Airbnb to be extremely low and potentially non-existent.
This Airbnb has a nightly rate of ~$350 and a cleaning fee of $199. If we assume that the average guest books for 3 nights the host is getting ~$1,220 after Airbnb fees ($350 * 0.</description></item><item><title>Ride sharing ride bailing</title><link>/2017/11/20/ride-sharing-ride-bailing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/11/20/ride-sharing-ride-bailing/</guid><description>One of the more frustrating modern, first-world problems is booking a Lyft or an Uber ride and having the driver cancel the ride a soon as they find out where you’re going. While against policy it is a rational decision by the driver. Why agree to a trip somewhere where it&amp;rsquo;ll be difficult to pick up another passenger and then have to return to where you started and incur a toll?</description></item><item><title>The sharing economy and human behavior</title><link>/2015/03/21/the-sharing-economy-and-human-behavior/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2015/03/21/the-sharing-economy-and-human-behavior/</guid><description>The sharing/rental economy is getting stronger and stronger and will have a massive impact on societies - especially cities. One thing that’s been on my mind is how it will fit into human behavior and biases. We’re so used to making infrequent or one time payments and then owning something that moving to a rental or sharing model might be difficult. For example, I don’t own a car and mostly rely on a combination of public transportation and CitIBike to get around.</description></item><item><title>Books are insanely cheap</title><link>/2014/08/11/books-are-insanely-cheap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/08/11/books-are-insanely-cheap/</guid><description>While the pricing battle between Amazon and Hachette rages on, I’ve been thinking about the relationship between price and value. A typical ebook on Amazon costs $9.99 while a movie in a theater, especially one in New York, can cost more than $10. And yet the book takes longer to experience - a movie is over within 2 hours while a book can be enjoyed for hours. Or how about a beer or coffee, they’re two to three times cheaper than an ebook but are consumed an order of magnitude faster book and only provide immediate gratification.</description></item><item><title>Low quality? Start bundling!</title><link>/2014/07/29/low-quality-start-bundling/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/07/29/low-quality-start-bundling/</guid><description>In the quest to reduce the amount of stuff I own I&amp;rsquo;ve been going through various cabinets and boxes and trying to list everything on eBay. The most common items are old cables with no corresponding devices (or any ideas what these devices even are) and old DVDs.
Looking at the historic prices for these items doesn&amp;rsquo;t make me happy - a Lenovo laptop charger is less than $10 while a Raging Bull DVD is a couple of bucks.</description></item><item><title>Trained for discounts</title><link>/2014/03/02/trained-for-discounts/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/03/02/trained-for-discounts/</guid><description>Nearly every week I receive an $8 off $25 coupon from delivery.com. I’m sure the intent is to generate awareness and develop a habit but it’s having the opposite effect on me: I’m being trained to only order when I have a coupon. Couponing is tough - too little and it will have no impact but too much and you run the risk of training your customers to only react to deals which will result in you needing to have higher prices to maintain your margin.</description></item><item><title>Surge pricing ideas</title><link>/2014/01/05/surge-pricing-ideas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2014/01/05/surge-pricing-ideas/</guid><description>Every time there’s a big event or terrible weather, there’s a slew of complaints about Uber’s surge pricing. By now, you’d think that Uber customers would expect this to happen and yet they’re surprised when a $10 cab ride turns into a $100 Uber ride. I suspect Uber’s already done as much as it can on the messaging side; psychologically it’s just tough for someone to take a $10 ride one day and then a day later pay an order of magnitude more.</description></item><item><title>Why's the iPhone 5C so expensive?</title><link>/2013/10/01/whys-the-iphone-5c-so-expensive/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/10/01/whys-the-iphone-5c-so-expensive/</guid><description>Many people expected the iPhone 5C to be priced low in order to compete with the cheaper Android phones in countries without carrier subsidies. The news that the 5C’s starting price was $549 left many in the tech community surprised and concerned with many believing that the price needed to be lower than $400 in order to compete worldwide.
I'm definitely speculating but I believe the reason for such a high price for the 5C was to avoid cannibalizing the sales of the 5S while also framing the comparison to be iPhone vs iPhone instead of iPhone vs Android.</description></item><item><title>Pricing small consulting projects</title><link>/2013/09/28/pricing-small-consulting-projects/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/09/28/pricing-small-consulting-projects/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing some consulting work over the few months and wanted to share a pricing model that’s been working well for smaller projects. I’ll sit down with the client to understand the scope of the project and work with them to break it down into smaller, more manageable components. Based on this break down, I’ll estimate the time required for each piece and come up with an estimated total time.</description></item><item><title>Netflix profiles, why now?</title><link>/2013/08/14/netflix-profiles-why-now/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/08/14/netflix-profiles-why-now/</guid><description>Netflix recently reintroduced profiles so now each household member can get their own recommendations, recently watched items, and instant queue rather than being forced to share the same polluted profile. This is an awesome win for Netflix customers but it’s been bugging me that they didn’t do this sooner; it’s such an obvious feature that it should have been built as soon as Netflix realized that multiple family members would be sharing their account.</description></item><item><title>Discriminatory Pricing in the Post Office</title><link>/2013/03/05/discriminatory-pricing-in-the-post-office/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/03/05/discriminatory-pricing-in-the-post-office/</guid><description>I recently came across Jeff Jordan’s post about revamping the post office so it’s no longer losing more than $5 billion a year. Jeff suggests the obvious solution of raising prices but I think a more clever approach would be to start price discriminating. Everyone who needs to mail a letter has to pay 46 cents for a stamp but why not come up with tiered pricing. People who need to send something urgently can pay more than a dollar while others who only care that the letter arrives can pay 20 cents.</description></item></channel></rss>