<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>productivity on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in productivity on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Tools of 2020</title><link>/2020/12/26/tools-of-2020/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/12/26/tools-of-2020/</guid><description>Despite not being in the code too much these days I still spend a significant amount of time on the computer so thought it would be fun to share my commonly used tools. Maybe there&amp;rsquo;s something here you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with and it might be enough to encourage you to give it a shot.
Hardware For the first half of the year I used Ubuntu on a ThinkPad X1 but switched back to a Macbook (Early 2019 Pro) due to a variety of stability issues.</description></item><item><title>Giving Obsidian a shot</title><link>/2020/05/31/giving-obsidian-a-shot/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/05/31/giving-obsidian-a-shot/</guid><description>I tried using Notion a while back but rebelled against having my data stored in the cloud in a proprietary format. For a variety of reasons I want my notes to be available locally in a text based format. At the same time there&amp;rsquo;s a lot to like about the modern tools and I feel myself being worn down. A few weeks ago I discovered Roam and am sold on its networked thought model.</description></item><item><title>Embracing smartphone productivity</title><link>/2020/02/11/embracing-smartphone-productivity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/02/11/embracing-smartphone-productivity/</guid><description>Unlike a modern teenager, I tend to avoid using my smartphone for anything except consumption. I&amp;rsquo;d read emails but not respond, check up on Twitter but not tweet, look at my calendar but not schedule any events, and so forth. The excuse was that I&amp;rsquo;d be able to do these much more effectively in front of a real computer. Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve realized that while the above is true I can still knock out a ton of small and simple tasks on my phone and save the meaty stuff for the computer.</description></item><item><title>Stop procrastinating</title><link>/2017/03/09/stop-procrastinating/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/03/09/stop-procrastinating/</guid><description>I often find myself wanting to postpone something but after forcing myself to actually do it I discover that most of the difficulty was getting over the postponement hump. Especially these days it’s very easy to get distracted - whether it’s checking your email, responding to a few tweets, or clearing notifications on Slack - but it’s important to just focus on the most important task at hand. After starting you discover that the task wasn’t worth delaying and get an energy boost from actually finishing something.</description></item></channel></rss>