<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>finance on Dan Goldin</title><link>/tags/finance/</link><description>Recent content in finance on Dan Goldin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/finance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My Tesla stock trade</title><link>/2020/12/25/my-tesla-stock-trade/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/12/25/my-tesla-stock-trade/</guid><description>The above is Tesla&amp;rsquo;s stock price since its IPO in 2010. On its first day it closed at $3.84 and was relatively flat until earlier this year at which point it shot up closing at $661.77 on December 24. If you invested $1,000 at the IPO that would be worth over $172,000. I&amp;rsquo;m one of those unlucky fools that purchased Tesla early - in 2011 - but then sold it in 2015.</description></item><item><title>Stock portfolio hedging during the coronavirus pandemic</title><link>/2020/05/23/stock-portfolio-hedging-during-the-coronavirus-pandemic/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/05/23/stock-portfolio-hedging-during-the-coronavirus-pandemic/</guid><description>I have had the majority of my liquid wealth invested in the stock market and I wanted to share what I&amp;rsquo;m doing these days. As a bit of a background, at the beginning of the year my portfolio primarily consisted of the tech companies I&amp;rsquo;ve held for years - Netflix, Amazon, Equinix, Google, and Facebook. After the first decline I liquidated about half of my portfolio - my thinking was that I&amp;rsquo;m still long term bullish about these companies and they will likely emerge stronger but I should hold on to some of my gains and have a bit of cash.</description></item><item><title>More intelligent credit card merchant rates</title><link>/2017/12/14/more-intelligent-credit-card-merchant-rates/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/12/14/more-intelligent-credit-card-merchant-rates/</guid><description>While reading today’s Stratechery update on Patreon changing their pricing model I came across the following passage:
Of course this wasn’t great for creators: payments made for a creation released on November 2 wouldn’t land in creators’ bank accounts until some time after December 1; the reasoning, though, was clear — credit card fees. Here I can certainly bring personal experience to bear: credit card fees are really expensive (they are by far Stratechery’s largest expense)!</description></item><item><title>Using options to play Snapchat's quarterly results</title><link>/2017/05/10/using-options-to-play-snapchats-quarterly-results/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/05/10/using-options-to-play-snapchats-quarterly-results/</guid><description>I rarely write about finance but a decade ago I did a stint in finance and picked up a few things. One of these was the idea of options which are an interesting and powerful way to participate in the market. There’s a ton of information online describing how they work but a simple explanation is that they give you the “option,” or the right, to buy or sell shares of the underlying stock at a particular price by a future expiration date.</description></item><item><title>My Snapchat investment strategy</title><link>/2017/02/26/my-snapchat-investment-strategy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2017/02/26/my-snapchat-investment-strategy/</guid><description>Facebook stock price since IPO
Snapchat is expected to IPO March 2nd and I’m torn as to whether to invest. I think it’s an innovative product that provides a compelling experience but there’s a series of red flags - from the weird ownership structure to the potential slowdown in user growth to the growing per user costs. At the same time it may be the next social network. Facebook IPOed at just over $100B and is now worth almost $400B.</description></item><item><title>Investing in tech stocks</title><link>/2013/05/24/investing-in-tech-stocks/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2013/05/24/investing-in-tech-stocks/</guid><description>I initially set out to write a post to complain about how difficult it is for an average investor to “hit it big” these days by investing in a tech company at its IPO but ended up changing my thesis after digging into the data. It’s still possible to get the same returns as it was in the 1980s but it’s not possible by a long-term investment in a single company.</description></item><item><title>On business models - To collect or to fine?</title><link>/2012/03/05/on-business-models-to-collect-or-to-fine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2012/03/05/on-business-models-to-collect-or-to-fine/</guid><description>A few years ago, I was on vacation in Italy and spent a good amount of time on trains. Being from the US, I noticed that my ticket was not checked every single ride. At the same time, not having a ticket and being caught carried a large fine. Having the luxury of time, some assumptions, and some algebra, it’s straightforward to work out how to set the fine to make the two systems have the same expected revenue.</description></item></channel></rss>